<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The uncertainty of the art of physick together with an account of the innumerable abuses practised by the professors of that art, clearly manifested by a particular relation of the original and progress thereof : also divers contests between the Greeks and Arabians concerning its authors / written in Italian by the famous Lionardo di Capoa ; and made English by J.L., Gent.</title>
            <title>Ragionamenti intorno alla incertezza de' medicamenti. English</title>
            <author>Di Capua, Lionardo, 1617-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12934</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12278157</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12278157</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58557</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33546)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58557)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 132:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The uncertainty of the art of physick together with an account of the innumerable abuses practised by the professors of that art, clearly manifested by a particular relation of the original and progress thereof : also divers contests between the Greeks and Arabians concerning its authors / written in Italian by the famous Lionardo di Capoa ; and made English by J.L., Gent.</title>
                  <title>Ragionamenti intorno alla incertezza de' medicamenti. English</title>
                  <author>Di Capua, Lionardo, 1617-1695.</author>
                  <author>J. L. (John Lancaster)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Fr. Clark, for Thomas Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Ragionamenti intorno alla incertezza de' medicameti.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication to Robert Boyle signed: John Lancaster.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE UNCERTAINTY Of the ART OF Phyſick, TOGETHER With an Account of the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Abuſes practiſed by the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of that Art. CLEARLY Manifeſted by a Particular Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Original and Progreſs thereof. Alſo divers Conteſts between the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> concerning its <hi>Authors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Italian</hi> by the Famous <hi>LIONARDO di CAPOA,</hi> And made Engliſh by <hi>J. L.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Fr. Clark,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Malthus</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE ROBERT BOYLE, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>THE Fame of Your ſublime, and more than Humane Wiſdom hath begot You many Admirers; and Your rare and incomparable Inventions, makes all men confeſs, That You are He, who by Your New Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcoveries have given Light to, and greatly improved the Ingenious in their Curious Inquiries into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Nature.</p>
            <p>This incourages me to Addreſs my ſelf to You, Imploring Your Protecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on for this weak Eſſay of Mine, which now adventures to appear in Publick; not doubting, but that as You have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb facs="tcp:58557:3"/>
been pleaſed to let me enjoy a conſtant Influence of Your moſt eſteemed Favour, ſo You will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at preſent pardon the Boldneſs, and with Your wonted Goodneſs paſs by the Defects, which You may poſſibly meet with in this Attempt of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>John Lancaſter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Don</hi> Carlo Buragna TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>NOT many months ſince, by Order of the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> was held a Conſult of ſeveral Phyſicians, for the putting of ſome ſtop to the Abuſes and Errors daily committed in the Practice of Phyſick. They, after ſome diſcourſe thereabout, judged it moſt convenient for a thorough-examination of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons already propounded; and yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be propounded, that every one ſhould ſet down his Opinion in writing. <hi>Signor Lionardo di Capoa,</hi> who was one of the aforeſaid Conſult, was obliged therefore to write his Opinion in this Affair; and it ſeeming to him, that
<pb facs="tcp:58557:4"/>
this could not be done to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe without a diligent conſideration of, and ſearch into the nature of the thing to be treated of, <hi>viz.</hi> Phyſick; he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted himſelf of his Obligation with ſo much Learning, Eloquence and Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that his Manuſcript falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of certain learned Men, and other Friends of his, appeared to them rather compoſed for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe that take delight in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blime Myſteries of Literature, than to be kept up amongſt a private and ſmall company, as if the Author in the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof had purpoſed to himſelf no other end, but to ſatisfie the Command impoſed upon him. They were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of Opinion, that a work of ſuch excellency ought to be publiſhed in Print: and for that purpoſe ſo laboured with <hi>Signor Lionardo,</hi> that they at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to give them a Copy thereof, and to condeſcend, that this at leaſt, of the many and different Tracts which he has lying by him, ſhould be committed to the Preſs. And herein
<pb facs="tcp:58557:4"/>
they regarded not only the pleaſure, the Learned and Curious will take in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing this Treatiſe, but the Profit alſo, that may thence reſult to all ſorts of Perſons, eſpecially to thoſe that are wary and judicious: Since by ſeeing therein the variety of Opinions and Sects, with the divers, and oftentimes contrary ways of Curing, practiſed amongſt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, they may, without entring into the more ſubtil Speculations of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, eaſily perceive, with how great Reaſon others believe and are perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that a Profeſſion, ſo doubtful and uncertain in it ſelf, has neither Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor Principles, upon which others may lay any firm Foundation; and how perilous a thing it is for men to ſee themſelves in the hands of thoſe, that will have it ſo, eſpecially when Health and Life lie at ſtake. Moreover, who does not perceive how advantageous this Treatiſe may be to ſuch young men, as follow Phyſick, ſince by the reading of this alone, they may arrive at a more exact knowledg of its Nature, than by
<pb facs="tcp:58557:5"/>
turning over the great Volumes of the moſt reputed and ſolemn Maſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and may in an hour underſtand what way in the Method of Curing is to be taken by him, who, laying aſide cozening Tricks &amp; Cheats, intends, as his profeſſion obliges him, to honour himſelf by the help he brings to ſuch Patients as come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hands. Nor, ſhall they, or any elſe that apply themſelves to better Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, fail to ſee how many there formerly have been, and at preſent are, who both in Medicine and other Arts melt their Brains in the purſuit of that, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not, or not to be found; and as our <hi>Dante</hi> has it,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Trattando l'ombre, come coſa ſalda.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Treating of ſhadows, as ſubſtantial things.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But without my enlarging any farther herein, the Reader may of himſelf by the peruſal of this Treatiſe ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how uſeful, and full of exquiſite li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature it is, and that its being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:58557:5"/>
without intention of having it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, hinders it not from agreeing with the Fame of its Author, and with the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that all judicious and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding men have of him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58557:6"/>
            <head>The Uncertainty of the Art of Phyſick, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted by a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Relation of the beginning and Progreſs thereof.</head>
            <p>THERE is not indeed, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, any Undertaking that makes the Majeſty of a Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Valiant Prince ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo worthy of Regard, as his acting in ſuch a manner, That by his Wiſdom and Valour, the people committed to his care, may be aſſured not to be aſſailed by foreign Arms, or miſerably out-raged without Revenge. Nor, is it in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion an Action any whit leſs generous and laudable to ſecure them from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of domeſtick Enemies, who then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58557:7"/>
do the greateſt miſchief, when they moſt craftily cover themſelves with the Veil of Benevolence and Charity, and counterfeiting themſelves full of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and greatly touched with Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Misfortunes of others, lay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for them ſuch treacherous Snares, as can ſeldom or never be eſchewed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mortal danger. And indeed, what Advantage would it be to a man to come off ſafe and ſecure from the manifeſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils of War, and afterwards unwarily to fall into dangers, the more hidden they are, the worſe? And this indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſo much the more worthy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as the Miſhaps of that Ship are to be judged more grievous and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, which, having eſcaped many ſtorms at Sea, miſerably periſhes at her very entrance into the Port. The pious and prudent Fore-ſight therefore of our moſt excellent Vice-roy cannot ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently be commended, who, having with wonderful and incredible Felicity accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed the firſt, and defeated the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Attempts of thoſe proud and cruel Fleets, which, infeſting our Seas and Coaſts, threatned us with Fire and Sword, and having likewiſe cleared the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways and Roads of thoſe Robbers and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58557:7"/>
Murderers, that diſturb'd the Kingdom, and prey'd upon the Villages, does at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent make it his whole ſtudy diligently to prevent us, whom he has rendred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in the enjoyment of our Fortunes, from being ill treated in our perſons by the miſuſage of Phyſick: Which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every one has need thereof, as it may, when kept within the limits of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and our (although weak) Reaſon, be perhaps of ſome help to the publick. So on the contrary, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it happens to decline to a ſiniſter path, it proves more dangerous and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Mankind, than Diſeaſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And no ſooner were the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Accidents that had befaln ſome ſick perſons, and for which the <hi>Chimical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines</hi> were accuſed, made known to his Excellency, but he immediately ordered, That we ſhould with the greateſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence imaginable apply our ſelves to ſearch out a Remedy for ſuch Misfortunes, and alſo to preſcribe unto Phyſicians (where there is need) certain, ſecure, and ſolid Rules to be obſerved in their Practice.</p>
            <p>But whenever, ruminating with my ſelf, I reflect upon the Numeroſity and Quality of the Difficulties there are in ſuch an Attempt, finding likewiſe as many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58557:8"/>
in my ſelf, I remain confuſed and at a ſtand, either becauſe it ſo happens in all other affairs of great Conſideration, or that the nature of this Art not bearing it, it ſeems exceeding hard and difficult to give Laws to the things appertaining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. I ſhould therefore rather chuſe, without any more ado, by my ſilence, to free my ſelf from trouble, did I not know, that I ſhould thereby contravene his Commands, whoſe not only Requeſts, but even Signs, I ought without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and with awful Reverence to obey: By which, as alſo by the Benefit that may perhaps thence redound to my Country, being incited, I willingly enter the Liſts.</p>
            <p>Now to the end every Deliberation or Reſolution that is to be taken in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may not prove altogether vain and unprofitable, I ſhall employ all the ſtrength of my weak Underſtanding; Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in the firſt place, of the Difficulties, whereinto, not only Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but alſo the wiſeſt and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Phyſicians have oftentimes fallen in giving permanent and certain Laws to Medicine, an Art, of its own nature in the higheſt degree uncertain, dubious, and inconſtant. Then afterwards, gradually
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58557:8"/>
and with ſober advice penetrating more inwardly, we will purpoſe (as far as the Nature of the thing will ſuffer) the way to make a good Phyſician and a better Chimiſt. Nor do I at preſent remember any other Remedy, that may be able and fit to repair the perpetual and almoſt fatal Calamities of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>And to begin with the moſt ancient Memoirs, ſetting aſide how ſhort a time continued in <hi>India, Babylonia,</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> their device of lodging the Sick on the moſt frequented Roads of the Country to have them cured by Travellers. In <hi>Egypt</hi> where all the Arts and more Noble Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies firſt came to light and flouriſhed, only the Kings, Prieſts, and ſome few of the chief Nobility were permitted to give Phyſick to the ſick, whence by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethon</hi> were reckoned amongſt the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians of moſt profound Judgment <hi>Antotides,</hi> the ſecond King of the firſt Dynaſty, of the <hi>Tinites,</hi> who wrote ſome Books of Anatomy, and <hi>Toſoretrus</hi> of the third Dynaſty, which was that of the <hi>Memphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi> But afterwards in proceſs of time this Profeſſion grew common alſo with the Multitude, and ſo much was the Number of Phyſicians increaſed, that for every Diſtemper there was appointed a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58557:9"/>
particular Phyſician, who was permitted to cure no other, as is teſtified by <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> Father of the Greek Hiſtory, in theſe words; <hi>Medicine with them was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, every particular Diſeaſe, and no more, having its Phyſician: whence all the Country is peſtered with Phyſicians. For ſome are appointed to cure the Eyes, others the Head, others the Teeth, others the parts of the Belly, and others internal and hidden Diſtempers.</hi> The <hi>Egyptian</hi> Phyſick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining only amongſt private perſons, it is not eaſie to believe, how, falling from its ancient Splendor, it changed through the Lazineſs and Ignorance of the new Phyſicians, who were of ſuch ſmall parts, that, as the but-now-mentioned <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſaies, The chiefeſt of them at the Court of the great King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> when he had diſlocated his Foot, knew not how to cure it, but with their Arguments reduced him to a very bad condition. Therefore we ought without doubt to believe, That in <hi>Egypt</hi> the Phyſicians were, as <hi>Diodorus</hi> relates, prohibited to depart from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the ancient Maſters; from which, if any one happened to ſwerve, and his Patient thereby grew worſe, he was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſhed for it. <hi>For,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>if after they had directly followed the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58557:9"/>
Laws of the ſacred Book, they ſail'd of curing the Patient, no Charge could be laid againſt them. But if they went con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the written Rules, they underwent the Judgment of Death.</hi> And really it was no ſmall good Fortune of <hi>Galens</hi> (to ſay nothing at preſent of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and others) that he was not born in thoſe times, and in that Countrey: For he would not ſo eaſily have eſcaped Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if contemning, as it were, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Authority of the Law, he ſhould have had the boldneſs to utter theſe words, <hi>I obſerve this not only in the writings of</hi> Hippocrates, <hi>but in all the Books of the Ancients, that I am not eaſily drawn to believe what any one of them has left written, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I have firſt well examined by the Teſt of Experience and Reaſon, whether, what they have delivered, be true or falſe.</hi> And that he was well verſed in Logick, is ſeen by ſuch Weapons as he uſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf withal, as Commenting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ancients, and reporting their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions intangled and obumbrated, to the end they might not contradict his own. A Cuſtom, which thoſe Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that tread in the ſame ſteps, have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and ſtill do follow, and which does in ſuch a manner deform his ſayings,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58557:10"/>
and alſo thoſe of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> that they oftentimes clearly appear to have written quite contrary to their firſt Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And perhaps the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their own Law, acted maliciouſly in the ſame manner, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb; <hi>Fatta la legge penſata la Malizia: No ſooner is the Law made, but ways are found out to evade it.</hi> And to ſuch a pitch peradventure did their neglected Boldneſs arrive, that their uſual falling preſently to Purgations, and for the moſt part with ill ſucceſs, forced them (their firſt Law being antiquated) to remedy it by publiſhing a new one, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in theſe Words; <hi>The Phyſicians may after the fourth day ſtir the humors, but if they will do it ſooner, at their own peril be it.</hi> Which Simplicity, I believe found not many Abettors, if they conſidered, how often Diſeaſes happen, that on the very firſt day need violent Remedies. But what a Fool would that Phyſician have been, that ſhould have procured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers Life with his own death?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grecians,</hi> who out-went all other Nations, as in Arts and Sciences, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Civil Prudence, having regard perhaps to ſuch inconveniences, would not impoſe any poſitive Laws upon Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58557:10"/>
or thoſe that profeſſed it, chuſing rather, that Infamy ſhould be the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Phyſicians, by whoſe fault the Sick ſhould miſcarry: For ſaies <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, There is no penalty ſet upon the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſers of Phyſick, only in theſe Cities, but that of Infamy.</hi> Which to thoſe that take their Reputation to heart, is more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and tedious, than any other Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which Cuſtom is manifeſtly ſhewn by <hi>Philemon,</hi> when he ſaies,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, <hi>Only the Phyſician and the Judge are permitted to kill others without being put to death.</hi> This alſo pleaſed the divine <hi>Plato,</hi> who thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in his Common-wealth; <hi>The Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian ſhall not be ſubject to any Penalty, if a Patient, taken in hand by him, dies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his beſt endeavour.</hi> To which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion <hi>Lucian</hi> comes very near, where he ſaies: <hi>By how much the Art of Phyſick is worthy of greater honour, and more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to Life than others, by ſo much ſhould the Profeſſors thereof have greater Liberty; and it is convenient that it ſhould enjoy ſome priviledge, nor ought a Doctrine, conſecrated
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58557:11"/>
to the Gods, and the Exerciſe of the moſt intelligent men, to be reſtrained, or ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by any power, or brought under the ſervitude of the Laws, or under the fear and penalties of Tribunals.</hi> And altho' among the <hi>Grecians</hi> the <hi>Athenians</hi> alone prohibited Women and Servants the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Phyſick, yet is not ſuch a Statute worthy of much praiſe, not to ſay, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves much blame; Becauſe, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be declared, the Underſtanding of worthy Women has been ſeen, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Expectation, to undertake the moſt ſublime Studies, and Nature has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten granted to Servants Courage and Wit fit for a Philoſophick Liberty; therefore did they, not without Reaſon, a while after revoke this Law. <hi>Hyginus</hi> ſaying, <hi>That the practiſe of Phyſick was allowed to Midwives for neceſſity and decency ſake.</hi> Much leſs ought we to believe, that the Sottiſhneſs of <hi>Seleucus</hi> took place, for ſo we may well call his Law, whereby, as if it had been mortal Poiſon, he prohibited upon pain of Death, all the Sick Perſons of <hi>Locris</hi> to drink Wine, unleſs they had at firſt obtained a Licence from their Phyſicians: <hi>If any of the</hi> Epizephyrian Locrians <hi>drank wine contrary to the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians direction, tho' he eſcaped, Death
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58557:11"/>
was his puniſhment, becauſe he did contrary to what was preſcribed him.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth, which far excelled all <hi>Greece</hi> and the Barbarous Nations not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Military Government, but alſo in Politicks, thought it not convenient to commit, without reſtraint, the Care of mens Lives to the Cuſtody of Phyſicians; and therefore by a <hi>Plebiſcitum,</hi> firſt made by <hi>Aquilius</hi> a Tribune of the People (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were <hi>Gallus,</hi> or another of that name, I know not) and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded amongſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws it was decreed, that ſome puniſhment ſhould be inflicted on their Failings, whereby they might be rendred more circumſpect and cautious in their actings. We may never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs well believe, that this Law, or <hi>Plebiſcitum,</hi> altho' made, was never put in Execution, otherwiſe <hi>Pliny</hi> would have been to blame to cry out in this manner againſt the Phyſicians; <hi>Furthermore no Law puniſhes capital ignorance, no example of Juſtice done.</hi> To which he adds, <hi>They learn by our dangers, and gain experience by our Deaths:</hi> And at length concludes, <hi>Only the Phyſician is allowed to kill a man unpuniſhed.</hi> But there is ſomething yet in the ſame Author that touches more to the quick; <hi>The Ignominie of the Phyſician
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58557:12"/>
paſſes away, and Intemperance bears the blame, while they that periſh are accuſed of their own misfortunes-</hi> And for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I ſuppoſe, did thoſe renowned Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers that were by command of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Juſtinian</hi> employed in compiling the Pandects, purpoſely paſs by that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere and cruel Sentence of <hi>Paulus</hi> upon the <hi>Cornelian</hi> Law againſt Murderers; <hi>If a man die of the Medicine given him for his health or the recovery of his Diſtemper, he that gave it, were he of Quality, ſhall be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; if of meaner Condition, let him be put to death.</hi> Which Sentence in the judgment of that great Soul of the Civil Law, <hi>Jacobus Cujacius,</hi> could not properly be reduced to the aforeſaid <hi>Cornelian</hi> Law; foraſmuch, ſaies he, as the Phyſician <hi>ſanandi, non nocendi animo dedit.</hi> And altho' the ſame Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers regiſtred both in the Inſtitutes and in the Digeſts, not only the aforeſaid Head of the <hi>Aquilian</hi> Law, but alſo the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian; Tho' the event of Mortality ought not to be imputed to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, yet what he commits out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, is to be laid to his charge, neither is the Deceiver to go unpuniſhed under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of humane frailty.</hi> Yet were theſe Statutes nevertheleſs rarely executed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' not only <hi>Pliny,</hi> but very many alſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58557:12"/>
after him, renewing in a more bitter man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ſame Complaints, brought Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations againſt them: Amongſt whom the moſt learned <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>Leonicenus</hi> writes thus; <hi>I have again bewail'd the folly of mankind, that has ſo long ſuffered beſotted Ignorance to reign, and all the while buys the hope of life from them, who are the real cauſes of certain death. Ludovicus Vives</hi> alſo cries out thus, <hi>Their Miſcarriages and Errors,</hi> ſpeaking of the Phyſicians, <hi>not only go unpuniſh'd, but are alſo recompenced with Fees. Baptiſta Mantuanus</hi> likewiſe has theſe words of them
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>His, etſitenebras palpant, eſt facta poteſtas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Excruciandi aegros, homineſque impune necandi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tho' blind with ignorance, yet ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free they</l>
                  <l>The Sick torment, and men (unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd) ſlay.</l>
               </q>
And an <hi>Italian</hi> Satyriſt ſporting with the Title <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſaies to the ſame purpoſe of the Phyſician,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ma poiche un talci puo donar la morte</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Senza punizione, e ſenza pena,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, che fi gentil titol riporte.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58557:13"/>Since Doctors have free liberty to cauſe</l>
                  <l>Our death, not fearing Puniſhment or Laws,</l>
                  <l>Our Hangman may this noble Title bear.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And our Academick in his moſt choice Dialogue ſaies in like manner of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cians; <hi>Hoc tamen ipſo ſecuri, quod nulla ſit lex quae puniat inſcitiam capitalem; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movero cum mercede gratia referatur.</hi> And another;
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Carnifici Medicus par eſt; nam caedit uterque</l>
                     <l>Impune, &amp; merces caedis utrique datur.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hangman and Doctor herein alike fare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Both kill unpuniſh'd, both rewarded are.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And another Author,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si quaecunque ſua plectuntur crimina lege,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quas, Medici, maneant modo veſtra pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acula poenas?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui plerumque ipſo facitis medicamine morbum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et diro ante diem aegros demittitis orco?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scilicet hoc vobis indulſit opinio, rerum</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na potens. Clades inferre impune per orbem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58557:13"/>
                        <hi>Mercedemque alieno obitu, laudemque pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If to each Crime its puniſhment be due,</l>
                     <l>What pain, Phyſicians, is enough for you?</l>
                     <l>Who with your Drugs Diſeaſes fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently</l>
                     <l>Do cauſe, and th' Sick before their time to dy?</l>
                     <l>This hath Opinion, which the whole World ſways,</l>
                     <l>Indulg'd to you, by others harms to raiſe</l>
                     <l>Your ſelves, and by their deaths, to merit Praiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And altho' <hi>Maximinus</hi> condemned to death all his Phyſicians, becauſe they had neither wholly healed him of his wounds, nor eaſed him of the pain, yet cannot the example of ſuch a Tyrant give vigor to any Law; nor was he leſs blamed for this, than for his other Cruelties, by the Writers of that Age, as alſo <hi>Alexander</hi> was deſervedly ſtiled cruel, for having unjuſtly cauſed <hi>Glaucias</hi> the Phyſician to be ſlain, through a ſuſpicion, that he had not been diligent enough in curing his deareſt Friend <hi>Hepheſtion.</hi> As on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58557:14"/>
the Clemency and Humanity of <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpes,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended, who freely permitted the Phyſicians, already condemned to dy, for having reduced him to a bad Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be ſet at liberty by <hi>Democides</hi> a famous Phyſician of <hi>Crotona.</hi> But let not any one therefore believe, that the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians gained ſuch a liberty by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Rules; for it proceeded rather from the utmoſt neceſſity of the publick, and is, as it were an effect of the Art of good Government: for I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that even the memory of the Myſtery of the Medicine would have been utterly extinguiſhed, if Phyſicians had been proceeded againſt according to the rigor of Juſtice. And what man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, unleſs he were exceeding dull and ſtupid, or extreamly raſh, would ever have vainly ſpent his Time and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the purſuit of an Art (if Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which has not any certain and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rule in its operations, may poſſibly be ſo called) in it ſelf diſpleaſing, and hard to be obtained, and in its Events very du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious? I ſay diſpleaſing, for what can be more offenſive and diſguſtful, than continually to converſe with ſick perſons, and daily to ſee and heal the Miſeries of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58557:14"/>
others, and that many times without being any ways able to remedy them? It is alſo difficult to undertake, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uncertain in its ſucceſs; becauſe in the curing of the Sick, not only the skill of the Phyſician, but alſo Fortune and Chance claim their ſhare: from whence aroſe this common Proverb; <hi>A Phyſician had need be born under a fortunate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation.</hi> And O how exceeding often does it happen, that contrary to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man expectation, as <hi>Celſus</hi> writes; <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation is likewiſe fruſtrated, and that man dies, of whom the Phyſician was ſecure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> And <hi>Hippocrates</hi> himſelf, although eſteemed a moſt profound and skilful Phyſician, yet confeſſes, That he gained more Reproach than Commendations by his Profeſſion. And therefore it is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difficult, or rather impoſſible always to judge, whether the unhappy ſucceſs of of diſtempers proceeds from the ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Phyſicians, or from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the diſeaſe, or from ſome other internal Cauſe, into which no humane Wiſdom or Knowledge can penetrate. Moſt uncertain always and obſcure are the Symptoms of diſeaſes, eſpecially of the acute, according to <hi>Hippocrates:</hi> wherefore <hi>Celſus</hi> alſo ſaid; <hi>It behoves us
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58557:15"/>
alſo to underſtand, that in acute Diſeaſes the Symptoms of life and death are much more fallacious.</hi> Beſides that in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Animals are wont to be ingendred poiſons, and that oftentimes preſently, by ſudden precipitation and Coagulation; and the man, whom not only others, but even <hi>Appollo</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would have judged moſt ſound and healthful, may have within him Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthumes, and other ſecret diſtempers, which, when he leaſt thinks of it, may be able to cauſe his death, and that at the very Inſtant when the Medicins are prepared: wrongfully therefore are the Remedies blamed, and not the evil qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the diſtemper. And beſides this, ſome Medicines which are eſteemed good, and conducing to the Health of man, may oftentimes occaſion ſuch diſturbance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Patients body, as may bring on his death, before we with our ſhallow Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings can prevent it, as <hi>Celſus</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies. It will not therefore be the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans fault, if ſometimes his Patient grows worſe by his Remedies; nor can Laws e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver determine any thing herein. But come, let us grant, that a method of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring may by Law be preſcribed to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, how can they be puniſhed for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58557:15"/>
tranſgreſſing it? or how can the Crime be ſo clearly manifeſted, that they may be proceeded againſt in form of Law? And who does not ſufficiently know, how all Phyſicians are of contrary Sects, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually diſagreeing in their Sentiments? Wherefore being either always ſtimulated by open Enmity, or which is worſe, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Envy, or elſe allured by the love and Benevolence of their own party, they will, without any reſpect to Truth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the matter to the Judge quite otherwiſe, than in Juſtice they ought, and make him, as the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb has it, <hi>See the Moon in the Well acccording to their own deſire.</hi> Beſides that, the fear of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, which the Phyſician may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incur, will always keep him ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dubious in taking his Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even when he intends to operate moſt effectually; and thus being terrified and confounded, he will, for fear of hazarding his perſon, in the greateſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies ſtand, as it were, fettered, and with his hands bound behind him, or elſe, not to depart from the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Vulgar, however falſe and contrary to the diſtemper, will oftentimes make uſe of vain and dangerous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. A thing which, as it is well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58557:16"/>
by <hi>Cardanus,</hi> is oftner wont to befal the Phyſicians of Princes, than any others, who not only for fear of Infamy, but alſo of greater Miſchief, forbear mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe of great and unuſual Remedies. It will not be far from the matter to bring here an Example taken from the art of War, not much differing truly in the uncertainty of its ſucceſs, from that of Medicine. The <hi>Roman</hi> Magiſtrates ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pitied, than puniſhed the Errors of their Captains, and it is well ſeen to what a height the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> aſcended thereby; as on the other ſide, every one knows to how wretched a Condition the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> were reduced, by always taking contrary meaſures. And this was yet nearer to our times manifeſted by the <hi>Venetians</hi> to their exceeding great da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and with the almoſt Univerſal Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of their Republick, when they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly beheaded <hi>Carmagnuola</hi> for his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs, by which, <hi>Liviano</hi> afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſmayed, and following the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the unwary <hi>Proveditors,</hi> loſt the day at <hi>Vicenza,</hi> and was miſerably with his whole Army diſcomfited and cut in pieces. And perhaps the putting of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telli</hi> to death, was one of the principle Occaſions, that the <hi>Florentines</hi> betrayed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58557:16"/>
by <hi>Baglione,</hi> ſadly afterwards loſt their liberty.</p>
            <p>And here ſome one may not without reaſon object, That as well the <hi>Aquilian,</hi> as all the other Laws of the <hi>Romans,</hi> by us related, were not made for able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, whether Methodical, Empirical, or Rational, but only for ſuch popular Empiricks, as are Quacks and Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks; the Name of Phyſician being not only given to ſuch vulgar Empiricks, but even to thoſe alſo that were wont to caſtrate little Children, as may be eaſily ſeen in the Digeſts and Code, as well of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> as <hi>Juſtiman.</hi> And certainly it is to be believed, That in them alone the Ignorance of the Art took place, through occaſion whereof, the Laws againſt Phyſicians were ordained in <hi>Rome.</hi> But this fooliſh ſort of Phyſicians ought indeed to be ſeverely puniſhed for raſhly intermedling in a Myſtery of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as is the art of Healing, and blindly ordaining Remedies at the peril of their Patients Lives. Therefore I think it very wiſely enacted in many Countreys of <hi>Europe,</hi> that ſuch Fellows are under very great penalties forbidden to practiſe, tho' theſe Edicts are ſeldom or never exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. And indeed, with great reaſon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58557:17"/>
does <hi>Anneode Roberti</hi> ſay of them, what <hi>Tacitus</hi> heretofore ſaid of Aſtrologers, That they are <hi>A Generation of people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to the Enquirer, and fallacious to thoſe that hope; always forbidden in our City, yet never expell'd.</hi> And the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Roberti</hi> is but ſcarce enough, That the Knaviſh Aſtrologers do nothing elſe, but entertain the Curious with their <hi>Jargon,</hi> feeding them with moſt vain hopes; and the vulgar Empiricks do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their ſilly Secrets, and idle prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, hinder the Sick from taking Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of able Phyſicians, which Neglect coſts them their Lives; or elſe they do themſelves kill them with moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Medicines.</p>
            <p>And juſtly, perhaps, were thoſe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Knaves firſt degraded, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards condemned in <hi>France,</hi> who, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of curing King <hi>Charles</hi> the Sixth, reduced him with their Remedies to ſuch an Eſtate, that there was ſcarce any hopes of his Life. But in my opinion, that valiant King was not over-conſiderate, or too well adviſed, to hazard his Life in the hands of ſuch Quacks and Cheats; and he ſhould, at their firſt offering to cure his Diſtempers, immediately, and without Experimenting their Remedies, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58557:17"/>
their promiſes, have puniſhed them for their Temerity and fooliſh bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if it were not the ill Will, and Craft of the ſpiteful Phyſicians of thoſe times, which made things go ſo ill with thoſe wretched Creatures.</p>
            <p>But how ſhould it ever be poſſible for either the people, or Magiſtrates, who, for the moſt part underſtand little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereof, to ſettle the practiſe of Phyſick by firm and durable Laws, when the wiſeſt and skilfulleſt Phyſicians, who with long Study, and much pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe have ſearched far into it, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver arrive thereunto? The Inventor, as 'tis thought, or at leaſt the moſt ancient Writer of Phyſick was <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> and he, as teſtifies <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> or whoever elſe was the Author of the Epiſtle to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus,</hi> preſcribed many Rules to be obſerved in the practiſe of Healing; but ſoon finding them not to be exact, moſt gently diſpenſed with them. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaies the Epiſtolizer of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Therefore we may ſay with the <hi>Toſcan</hi> Lyrick, that he
<q>
                  <l>Solchi onde, in rena fondi, e ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riva in vento.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58557:18"/>Plows th' Waves, builds on the Sand, and writes i' th' Wind.</l>
               </q>
Who vainly wearys himſelf with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring after the eſtabliſhment of ſuch Rules. And if any one ſhall deſire to have this made clear unto him, I ſhall with the beſt ordered Diſcourſe I can, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to demonſtrate to him the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereof.</p>
            <p>The Art of Medicine is at this day ſo greatly increaſed and advanced, that it ſeems to ſtrive for Superiority with the moſt illuſtrious and moſt noble Studies, its Juriſdiction to penetrate even into the moſt remote and extreme Confines of Nature; whereas it was at firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained within the narrow Limits of a few Plants, as (to ſay nothing of others) is acknowledged by the ancient Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Homer,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: whereunto agrees our <hi>Seneca; Medicina quondam pancarum fuit Scientia Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Thus in that pleaſant, and above all others, happy Age,
<q>
                  <l>—When Milk for food</l>
                  <l>Had the Infant World, whoſe Cradle was a Wood.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58557:18"/>And then thoſe firſt men lived free from fear</l>
                  <l>Of ſcorching Feavers, tho' as yet by Herbs,</l>
                  <l>Or Phyſicks skill they unaſſiſted were.</l>
               </q>
Either becauſe they had then little need of Phyſick, <hi>Firmis adhuc, ſolidiſque cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus, &amp; facili cibo, nec per artem, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatemque corrupto:</hi> Or, becauſe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, as all other (even the greateſt) things here below was to take its riſe from very weak beginnings; men at that time uſing ſuch Remedies as they found out either by chance, or by obſerving the brute Beaſts, or by their own Induſtry. Whence it is rationally to be believed, That <hi>Agenor</hi> and <hi>Chiron,</hi> held by ſome for the moſt ancient of all Phyſicians, made uſe only of Plants in their Cures: <hi>The</hi> Tyrians <hi>preſerve their firſt fruits for</hi> Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, <hi>the</hi> Magnetians <hi>for</hi> Chiron, <hi>ſaid to be the firſt that ever practiſed Phyſick: For that by the uſe of Roots and Herbs they cured the Sick.</hi> And of <hi>Chiron,</hi> the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out of the <hi>Chironian Panacea,</hi> or <hi>All-heal,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>The healing Root was <hi>Centaure,</hi> ſo call'd</l>
                  <l>From the fain'd <hi>Centaure Chiron, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi>'s Son,</l>
                  <l>Who found it firſt on ſnowy <hi>Polion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58557:19"/>
               <hi>Euſtathius</hi> declares, That being wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Hand, or as <hi>Pliny</hi> would have it, in the Foot, he found out the way of Curing by Herbs. And to ſay nothing of <hi>Mercury,</hi> who taught <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes,</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> ſings the uſe of the herb <hi>Moly,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>This ſaid, from th' earth a Medicine <hi>Mercury</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dig'd up, and taught the uſe thereof to me.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It appears, that <hi>Hercules,</hi> from whom the <hi>Herculean Panacea</hi> took its Name, cured only with Plants; as alſo did <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Arabus,</hi> and <hi>Cadmus,</hi> and <hi>Bacchus,</hi> by whoſe means, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us, that moſt powerful and pleaſant Medicine, <hi>Wine,</hi> was firſt found out, and brought into eſteem; and the great vertue of <hi>Ivy</hi> of marvellous ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy in repairing the Evils cauſed by the too exceſſive uſe of Wine, was made known to the World: <hi>Bacchus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was accounted an Excellent Phyſician, not only becauſe he found out the uſe of Wine, a moſt pleaſing ſort of Phyſick, but for that he alſo taught the uſe of</hi> Ivy, <hi>and caus'd his Followers, in the midſt of their Cups, to crown their Temples with it, as being that,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58557:19"/>
which by its coolneſs repels the Vapors from the head.</hi> Herbs alone were likewiſe made uſe of by <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> the Inventor of the <hi>Aſclepian Panacea,</hi> with which, as <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cander</hi> ſings, he Cured <hi>Iolas</hi> the Son of <hi>Iphicles,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>The <hi>Phlegyan All-heal</hi> firſt <hi>Paieon</hi> took,</l>
                  <l>As on the banks it grew of a black Brook,</l>
                  <l>Which he to cure <hi>Amphitruo</hi>'s Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child us'd.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And as his Commentator relates, he was wont to uſe it in the Cure of his other Patients: <hi>Aſclepius was ſaid to make uſe of this herb</hi> (meaning <hi>All-heal) who was the Son of</hi> Korones <hi>the Siſter of</hi> Phlegys, <hi>the Phyſician</hi> Aeſculapius. And ſo did <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaon</hi> and <hi>Melampus,</hi> who, as we read in <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> made uſe of <hi>Hellebore</hi> in Curing the Daughter of <hi>Proetus,</hi> King of the <hi>Argives.</hi> Nor did <hi>Podalirius</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaon</hi> uſe any thing but Herbs to heal the Wounds of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Army; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Trojan</hi> War, <hi>Medea,</hi> as <hi>Diodorus</hi> relates, cured with Herbs the wounds of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon, Atalanta, Laertes,</hi> and the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiades: Jaſon, Laertes, Atalanta, and they who were called the Theſpiades, all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58557:20"/>
theſe they report were cured by</hi> Medea <hi>with certain Roots and herbs.</hi> And <hi>Tryphon,</hi> according to <hi>Plutarch,</hi> highly extolled and praiſed the Ancients, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Whence they, having very often tried and proved their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, gave, as <hi>Manilius</hi> ſings, the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the Art of Curing,
<q>
                  <l>Experience through divers chances brought</l>
                  <l>Forth Art, the way firſt by example taught.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But as Medicines were at firſt but few and ſimple, ſo alſo few and ſimple ought the Rules of Phyſick then to be: whence by reaſon of the Errors, whereinto Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience might eaſily fall, it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that ſuch Rules, altho' very few, ſhould frequently change, the firſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines daily changing and growing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thus began the Art of Phyſick at the very firſt to manifeſt its Inconſtancy. But it did not long thus remain in the hands of ſimple perſons, ere Philoſophers began by degrees to put in their fingers; who at firſt, as is to be believed, were drawn thereunto by meer Curioſity, and a deſire of ſearching out the cauſe of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; but by little and little advancing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58557:20"/>
and going forwards, they arrived at length to this, that blaming, as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and perilous, the ancient ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Curing, they laid the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of rational Phyſick. And although <hi>Euſtathius</hi> makes <hi>Podalirius</hi> the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor thereof, yet it ſeems, by what <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſimachus</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> relates That this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ought to be attributed to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aeſculapius; Our Fore-father</hi> Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius (<hi>as the Poets ſay, and I believe was the firſt that ever methodized the Art of Phyſick. And therefore the whole Art of Phyſick is governed by that God.</hi> And he had alſo ſaid before this, <hi>The knowledg of what agrees with the Body in reference to Fulneſs and Emptineſs, and he that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes in thoſe things the good and bad agreement, he is the moſt skilful Phyſician. And he that makes ſuch a change, that for one Agreement there ſhall be another; and where there is not a Sympathy, which ought to be, knows how to cauſe one, and take away that which was there before, he is to be accounted a good Artiſt. For whatever Contraries there are in the body, ought to be made to agree one with another; Cold with Heat, Bitter with Sweet, Dry with Moiſt.</hi> Yet for all this, did not the Mutations and Uncertainties of Phyſick
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58557:21"/>
hereby ceaſe, but rather multiplied more and more: and as the Practitioners were various and diſagreeing, ſo it ſelf alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came various, and divided (as it were) into a thouſand parts.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time Rational Phyſick was in the ſtricteſt manner ſo conjoyned to Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loſophy, that it was (as <hi>Celſus</hi> avers) by the wiſeſt and moſt prudent <hi>Eſtimators</hi> of things adjudged to be a part thereof: and thus (it ſeems) it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the time of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> miſtakenly by ſome called <hi>Prodicus.</hi> Now he, as may be collected from what <hi>Plato</hi> relates in his Diſcourſe of the <hi>Gymnaſium,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was Maſter, and firſt Miniſter, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually falling ſick, through the neceſſity, he had at that time, applied himſelf with great fervency, and the utmoſt of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to the cultivating of Phyſick, and joyning it to the Gymnaſtick, and preſcribing it ſome Rules, which he firſt found out by Reaſon and Experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan (it ſeems) before all others to give it ſome form of Art. And then it came by little and little to loſe its ancient Familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with Philoſophy; altho' <hi>Celſus</hi> and ſome others are of opinion, that this firſt hapned through the means of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> And from <hi>Herodicus</hi> it ſeems, that the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58557:21"/>
now-mentioned <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> his Scholar <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryphontes,</hi> and others learn'd the cuſtom of treating ſeparately from Philoſophy, the things that belong to Phyſick. And altho' ſome thought this a very good act, and of great advantage to Phyſick, yet can it not but appear to him, who ſhall ſtrictly look into the truth of things, that grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Harm enſued thereby. Foraſmuch as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Philoſophers not at all regarding to meddle with Phyſick, and the Phyſicians diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing groſly of its affairs, there remained little or nothing of Rational, but the Name. And to ſuch an height did that blameable Cuſtom arrive, that their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors pertinaciouſly ſet themſelves with all their might to defend it; and being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in their belief, endeavoured to make all others give credit to it. And <hi>Galen</hi> durſt ſay of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> That he had certainly ſhewn great Wiſdom, in that he would never intermeddle, as <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> afterwards did, in inveſtigating the Nature and Generation of the Qualities of thoſe four firſt Bodies, whereof the whole Maſs of the World, with all things therein contained, is judged to have been framed and compoſed; ſaying, that ſuch a Diſpute belonged particularly to the Philoſophers, and not to the Phyſicians;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58557:22"/>
who have then ſufficiently complied with their Duty, when they arrive to know, that the Healthfulneſs of Bodies is ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Temperament or Mixture of Heat, Cold, Moiſture, and Drought. But what could ever be imagined more hurtful and deſtructive to Phyſick, than this?</p>
            <p>Thus in tract of time the Love of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom decaying by degrees in thoſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, that called themſelves Rational, the Conteſts about the ill-managed Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſprang up more fierce and outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than before: for whereas at firſt their contraſting one anothers Sentiments, aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only at clearing the Truth, now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly plunged into Factions, and obſtinate in their deſigns, they never cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed contending, brawling, and reviling one another, and railing in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the very firſt Maſters and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Art were not ſecure from their Reproaches. <hi>Apollo</hi> eſteemed heretofore the God of Phyſick, was now ſcoffed at by the fooliſh people, and vulgar Troop of Phyſicians, who openly accuſed him of having been a Pratler, and a Boaſter; and above all they taxed him with Ingratitude; becauſe that having gained the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Medicine from the Humanity and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58557:22"/>
Courteſie of others, he afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himſelf ſo proudly and arrogant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if he had by his own Induſtry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any aſſiſtance firſt found it out. Thus this crafty Cozener, to gain the greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and the more to advance his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, having learn'd the art from <hi>Glaucus,</hi> who was an old Fox, began to play his Pranks, and to act the Aſtrologer, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a way to thoſe Tricks and Cheats, by which the Multitude have ever ſince been deceived. Others railed againſt <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> who was himſelf alſo a God of Phyſick, for his Inconſtancy, and little Firmneſs in curing; and not a few Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were alſo beſtowed upon him for his inſatiable avarice: Foraſmuch as he firſt of all, as 'tis reported, profaning the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable and ſacred Art of Phyſick, drawn by filthy Lucre to cure for a price, ſold to a ſick Prince a few Herbs and Roots for an infinite Sum of money, whereby he juſtly merited to be afterwards Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck and burnt by <hi>Jupiter</hi> for leaving to poſterity ſo unfitting and abominable an Example. And beſides this they ſay, That in all ſorts of Jugling Tricks and Cunning Feats, he far out-ſtrip'd his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Apollo,</hi> and was therefore afterwards believed by every body to preſide over
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58557:23"/>
Auguries and the art of Divination. They farther alſo add, That by a thouſand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures and ſubtil Artifices he perſwaded others, as he did his Father, That he could raiſe people from the dead; wickedly thinking thereby to procure to himſelf the Title of Divine. But to be brief, they in fine concluded, That <hi>Apollo</hi> knew little or nothing of Medicine, and his Son <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> much leſs: wherefore doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he could not perfectly teach his Son his own Art, he cauſed him for a long time to be inſtructed therein under the Diſcipline of <hi>Chiron.</hi> And he, after he had ſpent ſo much Time and Study, grew ſo skilful, that in curing a little Tooth-ach he was in danger to loſe his Reputation, had he not in fine with a quick deliberation ſet himſelf to draw them, which if not performed, who knows what might have befaln the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. And for his great Maſter <hi>Chiron,</hi> how could he cure others, who was not able to cure himſelf; but being acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded by <hi>Hercules,</hi> reſolved wholly to reſign his Life and Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to <hi>Prometheus,</hi> and ſo bravely to rid himſelf out of all his Troubles? And hence we may plainly underſtand, what Truth there was in thoſe ſo wonderful and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58557:23"/>
actions, which lying anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity boaſts of them. Thus peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do the ſpiteful Contradictors fable of theſe firſt Maſters; and that I alſo may at preſent ſpeak, what I think, it does not ſeem to me very dubious, That the firſt Inventors of Phyſick among the <hi>Greeks</hi> were certainly but very ſmall Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents therein; ſince that in after-ages, when the World with Time advanced in every Art and Study, their witleſs Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes about it, demonſtrated, that their skill was yet little enough. And altho' they gained a great deal of Fame and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in all parts, yet ought we not therefore the leſs to perſiſt in our Belief, judging, that at the firſt appearance of Arts to the ſimple and growing World, the firſt Operations of Phyſick appeared wonderful and Divine Inventions. And this was much more eaſie for Phyſicians, than for any other Inventors; becauſe all their moſt conſiderable Miſtakes and Errors being, as one ſaith, buried in the ſame Grave with thoſe that were ſlain by them; and on the contrary, nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of them, but their Experiments, how mean ſoever, on the living by them cured, they might without any great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition eaſily acquire immortal praiſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58557:24"/>
and honour. Beſides that, this certainly happens in the moſt wicked and infamous perſons, who as they are crafty and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, procure themſelves every where Favourers and Partakers; and being far from true Wiſdom, leave no Deceit or Cheat untried, whereby they may gain eſteem amongſt the Dregs of the people. It is therefore certainly to be judged, That they, whoſe Fame was ſo much trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about, were moſt crafty Juglers and Mountebancks. It is not here my Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to alledge thoſe numerous Examples, which I could bring both from ancient and modern Records; I will only not leave unrelated, how it was anciently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that <hi>Acron</hi> of <hi>Agrigentum</hi> once freed the City of <hi>Athens</hi> from a mortal Plague, by the great Lights and Fires, which he cauſed to be kindled therein. But that Fire alone cannot produce any ſuch effect, our own Eyes have certainly and ſufficiently taught us. The ſame thing is <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaid to have done in his time. And <hi>Toxares</hi> alſo had after his death Statues erected, and Sacrifices offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him with other Divine Honours; becauſe that (as <hi>Lucian</hi> tells us) at a time when <hi>Athens</hi> was more than ever annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and even diſpeopled by a raging Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58557:24"/>
he is ſaid to have appeared to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitele,</hi> the Wife of a certain <hi>Areopagite,</hi> and to have aſſured her, That, if the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> would ſprinkle all their Streets with Wine, the Plague would preſently ceaſe; which they having done, it ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly fell out, as he had promiſed. But here I find his uſual prudence wanting in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who fooliſhly believes it, and phancies, That this might proceed from the Vapors of the Wine, which, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Air, purged it, and freed it from thoſe peſtilential Qualities that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it. But good God! if theſe Plagues ceaſed not, till that, after a long Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Mortality of the people, the Malady had quite ſpent it ſelf; why muſt we ſay, That this hapned through the means of vain and helpleſs Remedies, and not rather through the weakneſs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of the Evil? therefore it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be judged, that the moſt crafty and ſubtile Quacks, knowing that the Fury of the Diſtemper was already ſpent, and that it was in the wane, to gain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Fame and everlaſting Renown, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly preſcribed a Remedy, that ſo the peoples deliverance might be rather at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to them, than to the Nature of the Infection. An Artifice, which is even
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58557:25"/>
at this day continually practiſed by Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians. But as for <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> he may well reſt contented with that Glory, which, for his having been the firſt that taught the World the Art of Tooth-draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is rationally given him by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Orator,</hi> when he ſaith; Aeſculapius <hi>was the firſt that invented the drawing of Teeth:</hi> Altho' the Cures wrought by him are ſaid to have been ſo rare and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, and thoſe in ſo many different ways related, that as <hi>Sextus</hi> the Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick wiſely reflects, they may hereby have been concluded to have been wholly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous: <hi>For our Hiſtorians going upon falſe Suppoſitions, report, the Captain of our Science,</hi> Aeſculapius, <hi>to have been touched with Thunder, not contented with a Fiction, which nevertheleſs they variouſly transform. Steſichorus</hi> reports, That <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the height of his Glory by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, with his Medicines, reſtored to life ſome of thoſe that died at <hi>Thebes.</hi> But <hi>Polyanthus</hi> ſays, That <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> grew fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, for that ſome, who were by the anger of <hi>Juno</hi> ſtruck with Madneſs, did by his means recover their Senſes. And <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> recounts, That he gained his chief Repute by recalling <hi>Tyndarus</hi> from death. And <hi>Staphylus</hi> affirms, That his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58557:25"/>
greateſt Renown was gotten by his joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, and enlivening the ſcattered Limbs of <hi>Hyppolitus,</hi> whom his frightned Horſes had torn into an Hundred pieces. But <hi>Phylarchus</hi> avers, That all his Eſteem and Honour was derived from his curing of their Blindneſs the Sons of <hi>Phineus.</hi> And <hi>Teleſarchus</hi> in fine will have him placed among the Gods, becauſe he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to raiſe <hi>Orion</hi> from the dead. But what Artifices, how loathſom and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſoever, did he leave untried, to be held diligent and circumſpect in curing? He (ſaith <hi>Celus Rhodiginus</hi>) would (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was alſo imitated by <hi>Hippocrates</hi>) even taſte the Excrements of the Sick, as if that were neceſſary to the finding out the Cauſes of Diſtempers; for which he was afterwards by <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> in his <hi>Plutus</hi> wittily called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Excrement-eater,</hi> and we may better hit him home by ſaying with our <hi>Actius Sincerus,</hi>
               <q>Eſſe idem poteris Merdicus &amp; Medicus.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But above all, highly advantagious to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> were Riddles, Sorceries, Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Sacrifices, and many other Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and jugling Tricks, which he made uſe of to impoſe upon the Belief of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58557:26"/>
ſilly multitude, feeding the Sick with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hopes of their recovery, when he only held them in ſuſpenſe with his Talk. An uſual Cuſtom at that time of every one, who would with any Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions practiſe Phyſick. And to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Medea,</hi> and many others, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampus</hi> by ſuch fooliſh Artifices and Flim Flams, beſides the great Fame he obtained from a poor Fellow, as he was, together with his Brother, became moſt Rich Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Soveraign Lords of two parts of the Realm of King <hi>Proetus,</hi> marrying his Daughters, by him cured, whoſe names (ſaies <hi>Apollodorus</hi>) were <hi>Lyſippe</hi> and <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anaſſa;</hi> but <hi>Aelian</hi> calls them <hi>Elea</hi> and <hi>Celene,</hi> who, either through the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much uſe of Wine, or by the procurement of the Queen of <hi>Cyprus</hi> falling mad, went together with their Siſter <hi>Iphinoe,</hi> who died before ſhe could be cured, feeding on Graſs, and lowing like Cows about the Valleys of <hi>Morea,</hi> and other Countreys. Of theſe <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Bucolicks;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>With Lowings vain th' <hi>Praetides</hi> ſtark mad,</l>
                  <l>Fill all the neighbouring Fields, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58557:26"/>But a Remedy was found out for their Madneſs by <hi>Melampus,</hi> who, as <hi>Dioſcori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> will have it, cured them with <hi>Black Hellebore;</hi> altho' <hi>Galen</hi> on far better Grounds, judges that it was <hi>White Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore</hi> which wrought the Cure. This Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine <hi>Melampus</hi> firſt learn'd from the Sheep, ſaith <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> or rather from the Goats, which, as <hi>Pliny</hi> writes, he kept, who purge themſelves by feeding on <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebore.</hi> Altho' ſome are of opinion, that <hi>Melampus</hi> cured thoſe diſtracted Ladies, not with <hi>Hellebore,</hi> but with the Milk of Goats, firſt fed therewith; and others ſay, that it was not <hi>Melampus</hi> the Goatherd, who reſtored them to their Senſes, but another <hi>Melampus</hi> called the Soothſayer. And <hi>Polyanthus,</hi> as it is related by <hi>Sextus</hi> the Empirick, and <hi>Eudoxus</hi> a moſt ancient Geographer in <hi>Stephanus</hi> attributes this to <hi>Aeſculapius.</hi> But however this be, it is not to be doubted, but <hi>Melampus,</hi> after many long Ceremonies accompanied with Sacrifices, and other Superſtitions, cauſed theſe diſtracted Ladies to be firſt waſhed in that famous Fountain of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Clitorius;</hi> wherefore in memory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there were engraven in Marble thoſe witty Verſes, related by <hi>Iſogonus</hi> a moſt ancient Writer, concerning Waters.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58557:27"/>Wherefore after this, a Debate aroſe amongſt Writers, differently judging of this Cure: Some attributing it only to the Sacrifice and Bath, others to the <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebore;</hi> but certainly, as far as we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that both the Medicines were made uſe of by <hi>Melampus: Pythagoras</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus in <hi>Ovid:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Who once has quench'd his draught at <hi>Clitro</hi>'s Well,</l>
                  <l>Flies Wine, and drinks unmixed water ſtill.</l>
                  <l>Whether the water bear a ſecret Feud</l>
                  <l>To Wine, or as the Shepherds there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Amithaon's</hi> Son, when from the Harms</l>
                  <l>Of raging Madneſs, he by herbs and Charms</l>
                  <l>Had free'd, he flung th' Infections of their mind</l>
                  <l>Into the Well, where it has ſtill remain'd behind.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which Cuſtom, the <hi>Homer</hi> of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara</hi> perhaps had reſpect, when he made <hi>Aſtolfo</hi> ſeveral times waſh his mad <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lando</hi> in the Sea, before he gave him to drink the Liquor he had received from Heaven to cure him.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58557:27"/>
               <l>Aſtolfo caus'd him to be ſeven times waſh'd,</l>
               <l>And under water to be plung'd ſeven times,</l>
               <l>So were his face and all his members cleanſed</l>
               <l>From that ſame filth, that had him ſo befrenfied.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But <hi>Melampus</hi> not content with theſe ſilly Tricks only, to render his Cures more famous and remarkable, brag'd, as may be ſeen in <hi>Syneſius,</hi> that he was skilled in the Interpretation of Dreams, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thence to Soothſayings, and giving all men to underſtand, That <hi>Apollo</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed him with the Art of Divination, and that he having bred up in his houſe certain Serpents, they had in the dead of the Night, when he was aſleep, lick'd his Ears, whereat he, ſuddenly waking for fear, found at Day-break, that he underſtood the Language of all Birds. As <hi>Apollodorus,</hi> relates, ſpeaking of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampus.</hi> Not any Art then had ever, I believe, ſo much Commerce with Lyes, Fraud, and Superſtitions, as the Myſtery of Phyſick, which ſo manifeſtly appears to every one, who has but the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight therein, that it is not neceſſary for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58557:28"/>
me at preſent to trouble my ſelf any farther about it. Yet will I not forbear to glance a little at the ſtrange and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Ceremonies, which the Ancients uſed in gathering of Plants, to the end that by the ignorant people their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines might be eſteemed more wonderful and regardable. <hi>Piony</hi> could not be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the day-time, for fear of loſing preſently their Sight, if they ſhould chance to be ſeen by a Jay. He that would dig up <hi>Mandrakes,</hi> was obliged to have a care of a contrary Wind; and before he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to dig for it, he made about it three Circles, and afterwards pluck'd it out of the ground, holding his Face towards the Weſt; but while he pulled it up, another was to go round about him, skipping and ſneering, and uttering, I know not what, undecent and obſcene Speeches; as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus</hi> relates in theſe words, <hi>They who go about to cut the</hi> Mandrake, <hi>let them take care of a contrary wind, and make three Circles firſt with a Sword, then let them dig looking to the Weſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But with far greater Ceremonies was the <hi>Baara,</hi> which ſome will have to be nothing elſe, but the very ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drake diged up by the Ancients. They firſt threw upon it the menſtruous Blood
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58557:28"/>
or Urine of Women, then having remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Earth from round about it, they tied a Dog to the Root, who, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by his Maſter, in running, pluck'd it up, and preſently fell down dead. This is thus related by <hi>Joſephus</hi> the <hi>Jew; That part of the Valley which encompaſſes the City to the North, is called</hi> Baaras: <hi>That place bears a Root of the ſame Name: In Colour it is like the flame of Fire; and in the Evening caſts forth a kind of Lightning. It will not be touched by thoſe that go about to pull it, but flies away; nor is there any way to ſtop it, but by caſting upon it either the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine or</hi> Menſtruum<hi>'s of a Woman. And then alſo it is death to them that handle it, unleſs by fortune the perſon that carrys the Root, ſo carrys it, that it may hang down out of his hand. But it is taken up another way without any danger, and that is this: They make a Circle about the Roots, for the hidden part of the Root is the ſhorteſt; then they tye a Dog to it, who, when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter calls him away, eaſily pulls it up: But the Dog immediately dies, as being a kind of Revenge for offering violence to the Root, for after that, there is no danger to any body that takes it up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Account much like to this is given by <hi>Elian</hi> in his Hiſtory of Animals, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58557:29"/>
the digging up of the <hi>Cynoſpaſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The name of the Plant is</hi> Cynoſpaſtus, <hi>which is alſo called the</hi> Bright-ſhine. <hi>Now you muſt know, that all day this Plant is not to be ſeen, but at night it ſhines like a Star, and glitters like Fire. Therefore marking the place diligently in the day time, they go away, and come again the next night, and then ſeeing the mark which they left there. But the Root is neither to be cut nor pull'd up; for they report, That the firſt, who, through ignorance of its Nature, touch'd it, ſoon after periſhed, Therefore they take a Dog that has been kept hungry for nine days together; which done, they bring the Dog to that part of the Root next the earth, and then faſten the Dog and the Root together, with a Rope tyed with a ſtrong Knot: then returning a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance off, they throw upon the ground ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral morſels of Meat, which the Dog ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and preſs'd by hunger, pulls with all his force to get at the Meat, and ſo at laſt plucks up the Root. But if it happen, that the Sun ſee the Root, the Dog dies immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and they bury the Dog in the ſame place, uſing certain ſacred Ceremonies over the dead body of the Dog, as having died for their ſakes; for then they may be bold to touch and handle the Plant, and carry
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58557:29"/>
it home; where, as they report, they make uſe of for many profitable Advantages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor leſs vain and ridiculous were the Superſtitions, uſed by the Ancients in digging up the <hi>Panacea,</hi> as <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> relates. And of <hi>Ellebore</hi> and many other Plants there is ſuch a number of Fables re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported as well by the ſame <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> as by <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> and <hi>Pliny,</hi> that if I would relate them one by one, I ſhould ſcarce come to an end.</p>
            <p>But above all to be admired were the moſt tedious and vain Ceremonies, uſed by the Prieſteſs of the Iſle of <hi>Lemnos,</hi> in gathering the ſealed Earth, as they are related by <hi>Galen,</hi> who being an Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, made an Elegant Deſcription there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. To which Artifices alſo the moſt witty <hi>Arioſto</hi> alluding, introduces the chaſt <hi>Iſabella,</hi> making the drunken <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> believe, that ſhe had a never-ſailing Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret for the rendring a man invulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to gain the more Credit to her aſſertion, envelloping it in abundance of Cautions and Conditions in this Diſcourſe to <hi>Rodomont:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>I know where an herb grows, which I have ſeen,</l>
                  <l>VVhich being boild with Ivy and with Rue</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58557:30"/>Over an eaſie Fire of Cypreſs-wood,</l>
                  <l>Then preſs'd between a ſpotleſs Virgins hands,</l>
                  <l>A Liquor yields that hard'ns ſo the skin,</l>
                  <l>That neither Fire nor Steel can do it harm.</l>
                  <l>Three times anoint your body with this Oyl,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall be a month invulnerable.</l>
                  <l>But then the Vertue ceaſes, then again</l>
                  <l>You muſt again anoint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving theſe things to perſons more at leiſure than my ſelf, and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our former Diſcourſe, it is almoſt incredible, how the firſt Inventors of the Art were ſlandred and back-bitten by the Envy and Malice of thoſe Phyſicians, who more than the reſt wounded the Reputation of <hi>Melampus,</hi> giving out, that he was the firſt, who, to the Ruine of the World, brought forth the evil and troubleſom uſe of Purges; and that, if it fell out well for him in the Cure of <hi>Proe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>'s Daughters, it was more by good Luck, than any prudent Fore-ſight of his. But to let alone <hi>Melampus</hi> for the preſent, and to return from whence we digreſſed, it is likely, perhaps, that long before <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodicus</hi>'s Medicine was ſeparated from Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, ſince we read in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58557:30"/>
Prince of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Hiſtory, That there were exceeding ancient Schools of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick in <hi>Cyrene</hi> and <hi>Crotona,</hi> to which the often by us mentioned <hi>Democides</hi> gave very great Repute, by whoſe means, as the ſame Author relates, the <hi>Crotonians</hi> gained the Honour to be eſteemed the moſt excellent Phyſicians in the World. But it is to be believed, that Empirical Phyſick was at firſt taught in thoſe Schools; and that likewiſe there divided into diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Opinions, cauſing divers Factions. The ſame thing alſo hapned in <hi>Rhodes,</hi> in <hi>Coos,</hi> and <hi>Gnidos,</hi> where <hi>Eurifontes,</hi> or whoever elſe it was, publiſhed thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Sentences, that were afterwards cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Gnidian,</hi> which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> oppoſing in his Writings, there aroſe the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that was ever ſeen upon paper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Phyſicians, or at leaſt the firſt that afterwards came to our Knowledge. And as for the other Diſputes of thoſe times, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> gives us an Account of ſome of them in theſe words; <hi>In acute Diſeaſes ſo various are the Sentiments of Phyſicians, that often times what one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, as moſt helpful, others forbid as harmful: And for this reaſon the Art of Phyſick ought to be eſteemed very like to that of Divination, becauſe the Phyſicians behave
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58557:31"/>
themſelves juſt like to Soothſayers, ſome of which will have the ſame Bird, if appearing on the right hand, to be an Augury of good Luck; but if on the left, of bad. But others again hold the contrary.</hi> Now who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever deſires to be more fully informed concerning ſuch Diſputes and Conteſts among Phyſicians, let him read the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Galen</hi> upon the aforeſaid Teſt of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and I queſtion not, but he will there find abundant ſatisfaction. Nor ought we here to paſs by unobſerved what <hi>Hieronymus Cardanus</hi> ſuſpects, that the Book, which goes under the name of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> concerning the bringing forth of Children in the ſeventh Month, is, as he ſaies, <hi>Forſan</hi> Eurifontis, <hi>nulla ex parte</hi> Hippocrate <hi>inferioris, ſi ex unguibus Leonem, ut in Proverbio eſt, cognoſcere mihi conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt. Hippocrates</hi> then muſt needs have rallied all his Forces, when he contended with one, between whom and himſelf there was, if we may believe <hi>Cardan,</hi>
               <q>In value none, or little difference.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And perhaps with ſeveral others, of no leſs parts than <hi>Eurifontes;</hi> of whom by reaſon of all-devouring time, which has
<q>Conſum'd their bodies, and their Works conceal'd,</q>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58557:31"/>
I cannot at preſent give any account. But the famous <hi>Hippocrates</hi> publiſhed his Works in that place, who, although he ſhewed ſo much Virtue, as made ſome think, that Nature and Art ſtrove toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perfectionate in him the <hi>Idea</hi> of a moſt skilful Phyſician, yet could they not render his Doctrine ſo clear and warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but that it was ſifted, depreſſed, and confuted firſt by <hi>Diocles,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Pliſtonicus,</hi> by <hi>Praxagoras,</hi> by <hi>Erophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> by <hi>Philotimus,</hi> by <hi>Eudemus,</hi> and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> and his Scholar <hi>Eraſiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who was held in ſuch eſteem for Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, that he was by many able men judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed equal to <hi>Aeſculapius.</hi> And certainly from thoſe few Fragments, which by ſome, who have written againſt him, have been preſerved out of his many Works, it is ſufficiently clear and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, That <hi>Eraſiſtratus</hi> was no leſs a moſt ſubtil Philoſopher, than a moſt Excellent Phyſician. He was exceedingly free in philoſophizing, and ſo great a lover of the Truth, that he often preferred it before his Grandfather <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> &amp; his School, openly ſaying, that the <hi>Peripateticks</hi> had eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing ſolidly about Natural Things. Wherefore his Opinions were for ſome Ages received with greot Eſteem and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58557:32"/>
by Philoſophers and Phyſicians of more than ordinary worth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they did not uſe much Blood-letting (which is wont not a little to diminiſh the Eſteem of Phyſicians amongſt the Vulgar) yet their Fame never ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inſomuch that even in the time of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> and afterwards, their Sect was held in far greater Repute, than any other. Yet was not all this ſufficient to reſtrain the Rage of other Factions, that roſe up againſt it under the Standards of <hi>Neſithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> an <hi>Athenian,</hi> of <hi>Cienus,</hi> called alſo <hi>Pruſias,</hi> and of many others, all eſteemed in their times excellent Heads, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of divers other ancient Sects of Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Phyſick. In the mean time the never ſufficiently praiſed <hi>Empedocles,</hi> no leſs ſublime a Poet, than Philoſopher, doubting, that he ſhould not otherwiſe be able to infuſe into <hi>Acron</hi> his Scholar, evident and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Arguments for the Mutations of Nature, wholly forſook the Rational, and with his utmoſt Endeavours applied himſelf ſolely to advance the moſt ancient Empirical Phyſick; which was afterwards brought to perfection by <hi>Philinus, Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion,</hi> and other moſt famous Phyſicians, whoſe Followers always ſtrove to ruine, and reduce to nothing all the other Sects.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58557:32"/>
Nor muſt I conceal, that ſome are of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That <hi>Acron</hi> gave the firſt Beginning to Empirical Phyſick, whilſt others ſay, That <hi>Philinus</hi> the Son of <hi>Erophilus,</hi> and ſome yet, That <hi>Serapion</hi> was indeed the Inventor and Founder thereof:</p>
            <p>Thus by degrees were the different Companies of Phyſicians multiplied, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one with all his force contending to defend his own Party, and overthrow the reſt, when in the time of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, there ſprang up with <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> another moſt famous, and moſt illuſtrious Faction. This not only aſcended to a ſublime degree of Eloquence, as ſome vainly think, but prevailed much alſo both in Philoſophy and Phyſick, as may well be gathered from the Writings of <hi>Celius Aurelianus,</hi> and others, who report ſome of their Sentences.</p>
            <p>But I my ſelf am at laſt grown weary of turning over ſo great a variety of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Schools; which ſince I have purpoſed to recount, paſſing over at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the leſs Famous, I ſhall only touch upon the more conſiderable, as I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto done; and in the mean time I muſt beg your excuſe, if to bring my intent, I ſhall be ſomewhat long in my Diſcourſe. I ſay then, following my begun Harangue,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58557:33"/>
That not far from, or even in the very time of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, againſt both the Empirical and Rational Phyſick, ſtarted up <hi>Themiſon</hi> with his new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who, as he rejected the Sentiments of all others, ſo would alſo give his School a different Name, calling it from his brief, clear, and well-ordered Diſcourſe, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical.</p>
            <p>But this alſo did the moſt Eloquent <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Muſa,</hi> the Scholar of <hi>Themiſon,</hi> no leſs by his own Learning and Induſtry, than by the Authority of <hi>Octavius Caeſar,</hi> cauſe, <hi>Proteus-like,</hi> to change its Form. Yet was it not long for all this, ere the Methodical Sect got up again by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of <hi>Vectius Valens,</hi> Phyſician to the Emperor <hi>Claudius,</hi> and Gallant to his Wife the Empreſs <hi>Meſſalina.</hi> Afterwards it mounted to an exceeding height, being in a great meaſure reſtored by <hi>Theſſalus,</hi> Phyſician to <hi>Nero,</hi> who would therefore have arrogated to himſelf all the Glory of inventing it, as may be ſeen in that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, which he writes to the ſame Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, wherein he begins to ſay thus; <hi>I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now eſtabliſhed a new Sect, which alone has firſt diſcovered all Truth: foraſmuch as all thoſe, who have heretofore practiſed Phyſick, could not find out any thing that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58557:33"/>
was available either for the curing of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or the preſerving of Health.</hi> And in fine, this Sect was not long after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, and brought to perfection by <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus</hi> of <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of how happy a wit, and of what profound Knowledg the Inventors of this ſort of Phyſick were, with the whole Company of innumerable Followers, we may partly perceive by what is related in thoſe Books of <hi>Celius Aurelianus,</hi> that are come to our hands; and alſo by what <hi>Galen,</hi> and other Authors have written of them, tho' ſparingly enough. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Themiſon</hi> was ſufficiently commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Pliny,</hi> and his Name adorned with the glorious Adjunct of Chief Phyſician. And <hi>Theſſalus</hi> by his Sagacity and Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs wrought himſelf ſo far into the good Grace and Favor of the Emperor <hi>Nero,</hi> a Prince (tho' extream cruel, yet) very intelligent, that he became his inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and familiar Friend; and got ſo much the better of the Phyſicians, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries, that he deſerved to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on his Sepulchre that famous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And a famous Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of our time, altho' a Rational and Galeniſt, could not (as it is related by <hi>Proſper Alpinus</hi>) forbear in ſpeaking of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58557:34"/>
him, to ſay thus much to his Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I could wiſh the Books he wrote</hi> de Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatibus &amp; Synchreticis, <hi>were now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: for by the Fragments which ſome have cited, he appears to be a moſt acute and learned Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whither I do find my ſelf tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, without having made mention of the moſt famous <hi>Clinias</hi> of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> who, in deſpite of <hi>Theſſalus,</hi> and all other Methodiſts, gave beginning to another ſort of new Phyſick, never before heard of? And why amongſt ſuch an heap of Phyſicians do I let paſs the moſt wary <hi>Charmis,</hi> who was alſo of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> and Founder of another new and ſtrange way of Curing. This man was endowed with ſuch high and noble parts, that he intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced his new and marvellous Doctrine into <hi>Rome</hi> with moſt happy Preſages, and to ſuch an height arrived the Belief of his rigorous and ſtrange Inventions, that in a ſmall time the chief of the Senate were at his diſpoſal. <hi>They governed Fate,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi> of the ſaid Phyſicians, <hi>Into which City ſuddenly</hi> Charmis <hi>got, coming from</hi> Maſſilia, <hi>and not only condemned the former Phyſicians, but alſo perſwaded his Patients to bathe in cold water in the midſt of winter:</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58557:34"/>
(O the Efficacy of the Art of Medicinal Perſwaſion, to which all other force of Eloquence muſt of neceſſity give place) <hi>He plunged his ſick Patients into Lakes of cold water; and we have ſeen ancient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Conſular dignity ſhivering and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering with their teeth, even to oſtentation.</hi> Thus ſprang up, and continued Phyſick until the time of the moſt curious <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Galen</hi> of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> whoſe Fame is known to every one. He, joyning to his natural diſpoſition, Geometry, Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Logick, and all other Sciences, which he judged either uſeful, or neceſſary to a Phyſician, and being encouraged by the perſwaſions of his Father, who, as he himſelf tells us, was ſtimulated there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by various Dreams and Viſions from the Gods, underwent moſt grievous fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues by reaſon of his continual Labours and Watchings, undertaking long and difficult Voyages, ſubject to many, and thoſe not ordinary Dangers, that he might attain to a more than uſual Eminence in that Art, wherein he cauſed himſelf to be inſtructed by the moſt famous Maſters of thoſe times, if we will give credit to his own Relation about it. But he indeed was not crafty and malicious, as ſome other <hi>Greek</hi> Phyſicians, but ſincere, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58557:35"/>
of very great Morality. In matters of Philoſophy he would never tye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the opinions of any other, always declaiming againſt that Cuſtom, as blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and unworthy a Philoſopher; and proteſted, That in following the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> (whom he always regarded as the chief and principal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Art) that he did not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his words, as proceeding from a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Evidence, but from a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor only, that is, That he did not give any Credit to the ſayings of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> but to the Reaſons brought by him. And therefore, where he could conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently do it, he failed not now and then maliciouſly to diſcover ſome of his ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes; blaming him ſometimes, as no great Obſerver of the propriety of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and other whiles as extremely dark, and obſcure, ſaying, That he often entred into Labyrinths without knowing the way out again, and that by his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and vain Stories he ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated the ſame thing over and over again, not obſerving the ordinary Method of Diſcourſe: and in fine he forbore not to ſay, That he was mean, and pittiful, and confuſed in his Talk. Nay, ſo great an affection he always bore to Truth, that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58557:35"/>
where it was convenient for him to do it, he ſnarles, and carps at as well the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Phyſicians, as thoſe of his own time, altho' they were of very great Repute, and notwithſtanding ſome of them had been before very highly extolled by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for their skill and Knowledge. He unmeaſurably jeers <hi>Aſclepiades,</hi> calling him the <hi>VVonder-talking Phyſician, Empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate, teaſty, and obſtinate,</hi> ſaying, That <hi>he underſtood Logick and Philoſophy as much as the Aſs and Ox do playing on the Bag-pipe, and that he was ſometimes plainly out of his wits.</hi> He accuſes <hi>Archigenes</hi> of words, ſaying, That he often roams about, never keeping to his matter; and that he is always childiſhly buſying himſelf in the idle Toys of Definitions. He exceedingly beſpatters <hi>Herophilus,</hi> whom he calls Coz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Jugler, and riotous fellow. And in the like manner he deals with <hi>Eraſiſtratus,</hi> affirming him to be obſcure and confuſed in his Sentiments. But this is nothing to the Blows he gives <hi>Theſſalus</hi> and <hi>Julia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> calling the firſt Mad-man, and <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalian-Aſs,</hi> ſaying, That he was bred up by his Father amongſt Women, who card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wool; and giving the ſecond, whom he makes another <hi>Therſites,</hi> the Title of Apiſh-fellow, and brazen-fac'd Conjurer,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58557:36"/>
likening him in fine to <hi>Aeſops</hi> Aſs. And ſo far did he ſuffer himſelf to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with this vain blaſt, that he brake forth at laſt into moſt horrid and impious Blaſphemies, fooliſhly depriving GOD of his Omnipotency, and ſharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending Holy <hi>Moſes</hi> for having attribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to him; ridiculouſly ſcoffing at the Doctrines of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our ever bleſſed Redeemer CHRIST JESUS, and impudently daring to equallize the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy of the Medicinal Sects to the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and invincible Conſtancy of the Chriſtian Saints; and yet <hi>Galen</hi> lived in an Age, when there was ſcarce any place in the World, but was continually illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the Miracles, which were eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where wrought by the Teachers of our Holy Religion: Nor could he but have heard of that moſt famous Victory, obtained by <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> over the <hi>Marcomanni</hi> through the moſt fervent Prayers of the Chriſtian Legion, called afterwards from the Effect, that followed their Petitions, <hi>Legio fulminans:</hi> whence it proceeded, that by the Imperial Edict a ſtop was put to the cruel Perſecution of the Chriſtians, and ſevere Penalties ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be inflicted on thoſe that ſhould accuſe them, or inform againſt them;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58557:36"/>
upon which account alſo was erected that famous Turret or Column in <hi>Rome,</hi> which reſerving even to our days the Records of ſignallized Virtue, is admired by all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Wonders of that glorious City. This <hi>Conradus Geſner</hi> Conſidering, could not (however unreaſonably parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al for him) forbear ſaying; <hi>Raſhly and impiouſly does</hi> Galen <hi>refuſe the Schools of Chriſt and Moſes, as founded upon no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, as if the Miracles which are both numerous and divine, of which we read both in the old and new Teſtament, did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all Demonſtration.</hi> Nor doth he here make a ſtand, but proceeds with many other very grave Expreſſions to reprove him. But to return from whence the zeal of Piety and Religion had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported me. After <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <q>But few or none ſo far advanc'd in Fame.</q>
Few or none of any great repute were ſeen in Phyſick: foraſmuch as within a little while after the true and perfect Method of Philoſophy, which already began by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to decay, fell totally from its priſtine ſplendor, and ſwerving from its right path, thoſe Baſtard-philoſophers ſet at naught the true Knowledge of the Cauſes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Events, and contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58557:37"/>
only with ſimple Logick, or to ſay better, with witleſs Sophiſtry, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed the phantaſtical <hi>Chimera's</hi> of Terms, and prattle, wherewith caſting, as we uſe to ſay, duſt in the eyes of the Multitude, they made them think Glow-worms to be Lanthorns, and would make every one believe, That they knew all, when in Natural things, it cannot certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be affirmed, that they knew any thing. But in fine this vain ſhadow of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, ſinking together with the Majeſty of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire gave the laſt plunge, drawing with it alſo Phyſick, as may be ſeen in the Books of <hi>Oribaſius, Paulus,</hi> of <hi>Aetius, Alexander Trallianus, Actuarius, Philotheus,</hi> and other Authors, who ſcarce did any thing elſe, but col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, compile, and ſometimes unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlate the Writings of others. But in them we may yet ſee, altho' not ſo much at large, the uſual Conteſts of the Art, eſpecially in <hi>Trallianus,</hi> who, being bolder than the reſt, more than once manifeſtly oppoſes <hi>Galen,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, prude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly enough avers, That it is indeed a wicked thing, not to contradict <hi>Galen,</hi> when the Truth requires it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58557:37"/>And it has always been obſerved, that as men have been more or leſs addicted to Philoſophy, proportionably more or leſs frequent have been the Conteſts and Wranglings of Phyſicians; which is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſign, that theſe Controverſies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from mens more or leſs examining the defects of the Art.</p>
            <p>But at laſt through the extreme Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who took no care to copy them, together with the choiceſt pieces of Philoſophy, and other Sciences, were loſt the moſt excellent Volumes, till that time extant of Phyſick; which were in the time of <hi>Galen</hi> grown to ſuch a number, that the very Reading, as he tells us, of the good and uſeful Books of Medicaments would have employed a man all the days of his life. And the ſame diſaſter did then happen to the Books of Phyſick, as the Great <hi>Bacon</hi> of <hi>Virulam</hi> obſerves to have befaln thoſe of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, which being carried along by the rapid ſtream of time, as by an over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing River, the lighter only ſwam on the top, whilſt the weightier, and thoſe of greater value ſank down to the bottom. Thus together with Philoſophy did Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick remain depreſs'd, when the <hi>Arabians,</hi> who having forſaken their ancient Faith,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58557:38"/>
to follow the impious doctrines of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and rebelliouſly withdrawn themſelves from the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, had with victorious arms taken and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack'd very many rich Provinces of <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> finding by chance amidſt the prey and ſpoil they got in <hi>Greece,</hi> ſome Books, applied themſelves with more than ordinary fervor, to the Study; and lighting on the Works of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and ſome of his Commentators, as alſo on thoſe of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> they equally attended to profit themſelves both in Philoſophy and Phyſick: But being ſomewhat of a ſervile and ſuperſtitious temper and diſpoſition, they durſt ſcarce ever look into the Book of Nature, and ſearching therein for the Truth of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Things, curiouſly examine and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether, what they had them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves experimented, did punctually agree with what thoſe learned men had before deſcribed; but like a poor flock of Goats, they unwiſely, if not madly followed them as Guides, blindly retaining all the parts of Phyſick, and eſpecially Anatomy, juſt as they found it: whence through the fault of the Tranſlators, or perhaps of the Originals themſelves, they ran into many Errors. Notwithſtanding from thoſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58557:38"/>
ſmall and dusky Lights of Philoſophy they contracted ſo much Spirit, that they dared ever in matters of very great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to front both the <hi>Grecian</hi> Maſters; on one ſide, to ſay nothing of other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, reſtraining the uſe of Phlebotomy, and on the other as much enlarging it by letting even Children blood, little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regarding that <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> had manifeſtly taught the contrary; againſt whoſe Sentiments alſo they uſed Purgations, where there were no Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, the Humors in the Diſtempers being yet crude. Beſides this, they made uſe of <hi>Sena, Caſſia, Manna, Tamarinds, Rheubarb,</hi> and other new Drugs not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore known to the Ancients. They in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented new ways of compounding Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and having, I know not whether from <hi>Egypt,</hi> or elſewhere gotten ſome Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the moſt ancient Chimiſtry, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring according to their ability to reſtore it, they enriched the Shops with many ſtrange and unuſual Compoſitions; and ſome of them alſo with the ſame Art attained to philoſophize about the things appertaining to Phyſick. Whence their Prince <hi>Avicen</hi> departed ſo far from the ſteps of <hi>Galen,</hi> as occaſioned <hi>Pietro Meſſia</hi> (not without reaſon) to ſay; <hi>That the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58557:39"/>
Practiſe and manner of curing uſed by</hi> Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen, <hi>is ſo far different from that of</hi> Galen, <hi>and the Ancients, that it ſeems quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Arabians</hi> not content to have deviated from the path, kept by the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Maſters, often alſo aſſaulted <hi>Galen</hi> with the ſame Weapons of Reproaches and Contumelies, as himſelf had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed to vilifie and diſgrace the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Phyſicians. And amongſt the reſt <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> in Terms certainly villanous, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, ſaies, That the diſcourſe of <hi>Galen</hi> is contrary to that of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and that it is full of infinite Errors, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Lyes; and that he caſt his Eyes only on the Branches and Sprigs, never prying into the Roots of Sciences; that he had little or no Wit, or Sagacity in any thing; and that profeſſing himſelf a Philoſopher, he nevertheleſs uſed childiſh and vulgar Reaſons. Whereupon that famous Galeniſt <hi>Valleſius</hi> exclaims thus; Avicen <hi>in many things on purpoſe differs from</hi> Galen, <hi>contradicting him arrogantly, not only in contemplative, but practical Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After him followed <hi>Averroes,</hi> who not only blames, and vituperates <hi>Galen,</hi> but alſo ſeverely reproves his own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58557:39"/>
               <hi>Avicen,</hi> exceedingly wondring at his having taken for his Guide a <hi>Grecian</hi> Babler, who was not of parts ſufficient, ever to arrive at the Knowledge of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural things. Whereunto he adds, That <hi>Galen</hi> was ſo weak and unskilful a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician, that Syllogiſms framed by him, were often found falſe in their principles, and faulty in their figures, and that his diſcourſe was like to the idle Talk and Quibbles of Buffoons and Jeſters. Nor were the <hi>Arabians</hi> leſs contentious, and divided among themſelves, than the <hi>Greeks</hi> had formerly been, altho' they did not after the manner of thoſe, ſeparate themſelves into parties, as may be eaſily diſcerned in the Works of <hi>Rhaſis, Avicen, Averroes,</hi> and other their Writers. And thus they went continually on, philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phizing, and advancing in their Studies, when by the command of the <hi>Caliph,</hi> and other <hi>Mahometan</hi> Princes, their Schools were all ſhut up, and good Learning pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited; and this by reaſon of the barbarous Government, they having long obſerved, that the Sciences, eſpecially Philoſophy, opening the Eyes of the peoples Mind, made them eaſily perceive the ridiculous Forgeries, and childiſh Simplicities of the <hi>Alcoran:</hi> Wherefore with Philoſophy,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58557:40"/>
Phyſick alſo decayed in an inſtant among the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and all Literature gave up the Ghoſt. But before this came to paſs, by the means and diligence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, the <hi>Arabian</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors together with thoſe few <hi>Greeks,</hi> which were then publiſhed in <hi>Arabick,</hi> were Tranſlated into <hi>Latin,</hi> however bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and unpoliſh'd, ſuch as was uſed in thoſe moſt unhappy times. And thus in afflicted and deſolate <hi>Italy</hi> began the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, and decayed Studies of Phyſick to riſe up again. But how violently then of a ſudden the Conteſts and Diſputes of the <hi>Italian</hi> Wits were awakened, he that is deſirous to know, may read in <hi>Pietrod' Albano, Gentile da Foligno, Taddeo,</hi> and <hi>Nicolo Fiorentini, Dino,</hi> and <hi>Tomaſſo dal Garbo, Giacomo da Forli, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>goda Siena, Giacomo delle Parti,</hi> and may other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>But afterwards the purity and elegancy of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue being in more quiet times arrived at firſt in our moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Countrey of <hi>Italy,</hi> and then in the other provinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifluous <hi>Greek</hi> Language coming about the ſame time from <hi>Greece,</hi> then for the moſt part ſubjugated and harraſſed by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Princes, Phyſicians began by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58557:40"/>
little and little to read the <hi>Greek</hi> Authors in their primitive Idiom, faithfully tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating them from their Original into <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> And then more fiercely than ever ſprang up the Conteſts of Phyſicians, which grew exceeding hot between thoſe, who on the one ſide would follow their <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and others, who on the contrary in defence of the <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> vigorouſly oppoſed the <hi>Grecian</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. And becauſe there are yet to be found in the hands of the Curious ſome of their detracting Writings, I have thought it not amiſs, out of one of them, intituled, <hi>Nobilis Socii Salodienſis praecertatio pro Arabum, &amp; proborum medicorum tutela,</hi> as briefly as I may, and by way of Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to rehearſe ſome things, which may ſerve as a Sample of the reſt.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe, altho' it undertakes the defence of the Barbarian Phyſicians, yet appears not in the leaſt to be barbarouſly written; and the Author thereof ſeems to me to be an able man, and very well ſeen in the Doctrines of <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> whereof joyning together many Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, he with exquiſite artifice frames long, and well-ordered diſcourſes. He begins ingenuouſly, and with a mind free from paſſion, induced, as he ſaies, by the love
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58557:41"/>
of Truth alone to contend with certain Phyſicians of his own Time, who, either to ſhew themſelves skill'd in the Learning of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> or through the over-much affection they bare the <hi>Grecian</hi> Authors, or to let others ſee, that they walked not in the common Road, made it their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to oppoſe, as the Proverb has it, the Pandects, and vilifying, and contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly treating the <hi>Arabian</hi> Phyſicians, endeavoured on the contrary with the higheſt praiſes to extol the <hi>Grecians</hi> unto Heaven. And it ſeems, that their firſt Motive thereunto, was only the ſecret ill Will, Anger, and Spight, which they bore towards moſt barbarous and foreign Nations; which they ſo far improved, that contrary to the expreſs Laws of good Manners, and the precepts of their own Maſter <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> they impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belched forth againſt them the greateſt Villanies, that the Malice of ſuch ſilly Wretches could invent, calling them now Cheats, anon Shallow-pates, and often branding them with like Imputations. Having prefaced in this manner, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to his diſcourſe, what is by theſe men in behalf of the <hi>Greeks</hi> objected againſt the <hi>Arabian</hi> Phyſicians: <hi>viz.</hi> That the clear and overflowing Fountain of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58557:41"/>
Phyſick was at firſt preſerved pure and without mixture by its Authors, but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling afterwards into the hands of theſe, ſoon became troubled and muddy; and that thoſe were the true Maſters and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors of that Art, and theſe Barbarian Caitiffs only Tranſlators, who without taking any pains, vainly boaſted of other mens Works, as if they were their own. Then going on, he ſaith, That they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the <hi>Arabians,</hi> for that in tranſlating the <hi>Greeks</hi> from their Originals, not well comprehending their Sentiments, they filled their Writings with Confuſion and Contention; and in Concluſion, he adds, That the Cenſurers of his time, proſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Followers of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> as ſtanding upon moſt weak and unſure Foundations, or being only covetous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mony, accuſed them for inventing ſo many, tho' rich and coſtly Syrups.</p>
            <p>But the aforeſaid Author, deſirous by a ſtrict Examination of them, to refel theſe Accuſations, brought againſt the <hi>Arabians,</hi> firſt explains the meaning of that Saying, to wit, That the <hi>Greeks</hi> were indeed the Maſters, and the <hi>Arabians</hi> no more but Scholars, and Tranſlators in phyſick. Hereby, ſaith he, they either mean, that the <hi>Greeks</hi> were of all Nations
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58557:42"/>
the firſt Inventors thereof, and the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> only Builders upon the old foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which, as he tells us, needs far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confirmation before it be granted, ſince he manifeſtly proves by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity both of the <hi>Greeks</hi> themſelves, and of the <hi>Latin</hi> Writers, That they, to wit, the <hi>Greeks,</hi> firſt learn'd it from the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or ſome other people; or elſe their opinion is, That the <hi>Greeks</hi> by putting the laſt hand to it, brought it to ſuch a degree of perfection, that it is impoſſible to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it any higher. And this ſaid, he fell again anew to diſtinguiſhing, telling us, That hereby they intended, either that by every one of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> phyſick was raiſed to the utmoſt height whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it poſſibly could arrive; or that they had all of them contributed their aſſiſtance thereunto; or that ſome one amongſt ſo many Maſters had performed this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit. The firſt he avers to be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe, and to have been in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s confeſs'd ſo to be by their Prince <hi>Galen</hi> himſelf. The ſecond, he ſaies, can never be granted to be true, by many and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reaſons demonſtrating it to be moſt falſe, which were it otherwiſe, yet would it be exceeding difficult, nay even impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ever to learn from the <hi>Grecian</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58557:42"/>
Maſters the moſt confuſed Art of Phyſick; there being ſo many Volumes differently written by them, that a man cannot run them over with his Eye, much leſs atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively ſtudy them, tho' he ſhould employ therein every day of his life. It remains then to ſay, That one alone amongſt ſo many <hi>Greeks</hi> has brought Medicine to its chiefeſt Splendor, and foraſmuch as we are aſſured by the Authority of <hi>Galen,</hi> that all others before him were often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled and miſled: and therefore, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imperfect, and without much Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, not greatly to be regarded. This moſt magnificent Honour and dignity muſt be attributed therefore to the moſt profound and more than human Wit of <hi>Claudius Galenus</hi> of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> eſteemed commonly the chief amongſt all the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Maſters; and that, not only by the Univerſal Conſent of his Partizans, but alſo in his own proper Judgment, which he was not aſhamed in many places vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloriouſly to affirm. Here our Cenſurer, loſing his patience, makes his <hi>Avicen</hi> brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter the Liſts againſt <hi>Galen.</hi> He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduces the <hi>Greek,</hi> expoſing his reaſons, and declaring his honourable Quality, and this he does in <hi>Galens</hi> own Words, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and tack'd together out of his own
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58557:43"/>
Writings, in which he extremely glories of his Birth, Education, Studies, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary progreſs in the <hi>Encyclopaideia</hi> of all Sciences, and divine Knowledg in phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, relating in fine, what he with <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> and infinite Brags, vauntingly tells us of his own Qualifications. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary with ſimple, modeſt, and humble words he declares the Life, Manners, and Studies of his <hi>Avicen:</hi> and as he makes the <hi>Arabian</hi> far exceed the <hi>Greek</hi> in Birth, and good Qualities, ſo not at the firſt glance alone, but by penetrating farther into the matter, he will plainly let us ſee, which of the two excels in Knowledge. And here he begins ſtrictly to ſift and examine <hi>Galens</hi> Works: And altho' he tells us, That he will elſewhere clearly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly diſcover his Errors and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, promiſing to collect them into one entire Volume, yet ſince he judges it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to his preſent purpoſe, he proceeds to give an account of ſome of the greateſt and moſt conſpicuous, ſaying, That how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever groſs and palpable they are, yet will not the Galeniſts diſcern them, when for the leaſt Straw that lies in their way, they preſently take ſnuff, proudly vilifying and reproaching poor <hi>Avicen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58557:43"/>He ſays then, That <hi>Galen,</hi> however eſteemed a moſt profound and acute Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, yet in that part of Philoſophy which is deſervedly held to be of greateſt import, and value, to wit, the Moral, he had as little Judgment and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a Blind-man has in Colours; and that this was the reaſon he ſo little practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. Firſt he demonſtrates him to have been moſt ungrateful to his parents, and not being aſhamed to lay open to the whole World the Faults and evil Qualities of his Mother, ſaying, That ſhe was ſo proud and peeviſh, that often falling into exceſs, ſhe uſed unmercifully to outrage her Servants; and that ſhe behaved her ſelf more frowardly, and croſs-grainedly to her Husband, than ever did <hi>Zantippe</hi> to the moſt patient <hi>Socrates.</hi> Hereto he adds, That he is extremely vain-glorious, and an unmeaſurable Boaſter of his own Excellencies: and this may without any other proof be eaſily learnt from his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he having filled them all with Praiſes and Encomiums of himſelf. And indeed, what greater vanity, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption can there be, than to affirm, as he doth, That none can fully compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the meaning of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> without the aſſiſtance of his moſt profound Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58557:44"/>
and that he alone had given phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick its ultimate perfection? and that the Gods, as if they were concerned, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his Honour, had taught him many Medicines, as he brags, when he treats of the Nerves of the Eyes, and of the Cure of wounded Nerves in general? and that he could diſcourſe for a whole day on the moſt obſcure and difficult Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, having often done it to his great commendation, when taken on a ſudden?</p>
            <p>But of what Honeſty, Conſtancy, or Juſtice, can he ever boaſt, having, as he himſelf tells us, given a ſick Child a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which according to his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Opinion, muſt have undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly kill'd him, as it did? Certainly he cannot but be infinitely blamed for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by any one, that has the leaſt ſenſe of Humanity and Compaſſion. Nor does it any whit avail him to cover this barbarous action with light excuſes, as that he did not herein follow his own Inclinations, but was forced thereunto by fear; ſince he ought, couragiouſly reſiſting, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo to do, to have acted according to Juſtice and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But our Author, having thus ſhewn him to be blame-worthy for his want of Morality, proceeds to acquaint us with his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58557:44"/>
Learning, ſaying, That he was as well skill'd in Logick, as a Tortoiſe in flying, or a Cow in dancing. For ſetting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at his beginning, to divide Words into ſignificative, and inſignificative, and alledging for the latter the common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Blictri</hi> and <hi>Syndapſus,</hi> he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſubjoyns, that theſe are no words. And beſides this, all Logicians acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging rationality to be the ultimate diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that conſtitutes man in his Eſſence, he on the contrary ſtifly holds, that Babes are not rational, but in time will be; which in good earneſt is to ſay, that they are not true Men, but hereafter will be ſo: which moſt notorious Error he fell into, for that ſeeing them prattle confuſedly, the Sot had not the Wit to conſider, that Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionality did not neceſſarily imply Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>in actu,</hi> but <hi>in potentia</hi> only, as the term is. Nay, what is more, this great man could not arrive to comprehend, That <hi>Rational</hi> and <hi>Irrational</hi> are terms abſolutely contradictory; and therefore he fooliſhly and childiſhly affirms, That the Brute Beaſts, which are all of them undoubtedly void of Reaſon, are more or leſs partakers thereof, calling man <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> only by way of Excellency, or <hi>per</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he has it. And from this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58557:45"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ves another Error, no leſs groſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>excuſable, nay, perhaps greater than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormer: That Aſſes, altho the dulleſt and ſluggiſheſt of all Beaſts, have yet full and perfect knowledg of this moſt difficult Aphoriſm of the Phyſicians, <hi>Contraria contrariis curantur.</hi> But who, for Gods ſake, is there among the Logicians, which does not fully approve the ſaying of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, That from Truth follows only Truth;</hi> whereas from Falſity Truth and Falſity do equally proceed? And yet the moſt acute <hi>Galen,</hi> manifeſtly oppoſing it, gives us cauſe to believe that he did not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand it. But what praiſe did he gain by that his moſt ingenuous Invention of the fourth Figure, gloriouſly found out by him to the ſhame of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the other Maſter in Logick? Certainly it has by all Logicians been diſapproved, and with reaſon rejected, as confuſed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for Diſputation.</p>
            <p>From theſe frivolous Toys of Logick our Cenſurer proceeds to examine him in matters of greater import, ſuch as is Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy. And he thinks <hi>Galen</hi> to be in Philoſophy more thick &amp; muddy than puddle-water; and this he manifeſts by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proofs: whereof I ſhall rehearſe only a few, not to deviate too far from my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58557:45"/>
intent. <hi>Galen</hi> then ſays, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirms, that Plants have full and intire Senſe, and an internal principle of Motion within themſelves; that Motion cannot be comprehended of us by the corporal Senſes, but by Reaſon only; that Crabs and Beetles have no heads, thoſe Animals only in his opinion, having an Head, which have ſoft Eyes, and not thoſe, whoſe Eyes are covered with an hard and criſtalline ſhell; and yet the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is manifeſtly ſeen in Graſhoppers, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, and ſuch like Creatures. Beſides this, he ſays, That the Head is not made by the Brain, that in Volatils the Neck and Feet are equally diſtant from the Heart; that the brain in Animals has need of ſomewhat to move it, which are the Feet, and that the Feet on the contrary have need of Senſe, which is given them by the brain; and that the one without the other is of no uſe or value; not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that Eels, Lampreys, and ſuch like Fiſh, altho' they have no Feet, have yet Brains. And here the wary Champion of the <hi>Arabians</hi> opportunely retorts upon <hi>Galen</hi> the ſame Weapons wherewith the other thought to have wounded <hi>Avicen: And ſince,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>mention begins to be made of the Brain, before we leave that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58557:46"/>
we ſhall add, that</hi> Galen <hi>(in the ſame manner as they reproach'd</hi> Avicen) <hi>wanted Brains himſelf.</hi> But how expert <hi>Galen</hi> was in Philoſophy, any one may eaſily diſcern from his diſcourſe concerning Hair; he obſerving, that the Hairs of the Eye-lids and Eye-brows are always at a ſtay, and do not encreaſe and grow, as do thoſe of the Head, and other parts of the Body, and willing to give a reaſon thereof, ſaies, That, as it happens in dry and barren grounds that the Graſs does not grow for want of ſufficient Moiſture, ſo the Hairs of the Eye-lids and Eye-brows by reaſon of the little or no Nouriſhment, which they draw from the other parts, cannot come to any great length. Now who in God's Name, does not ſee, that, if this were the cauſe thereof, the Hairs of the Head muſt much leſs increaſe and grow, as being root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in an harder and drier skin, than that of the Eye-lids? And it appears to our Author, that the nouriſhment of theſe Hairs inſenſibly exhales and evaporates through the exceeding ſmall Pores of the Eyes. The moſt ſharp-ſighted <hi>Galen</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaies, That provident Nature has given us Hair for an Ornament to our Body: But if it were ſo, to what purpoſe do they grow in thoſe parts, which Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58557:46"/>
obliges us not to name? Beſides that Nature would greatly have injured Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by depriving them in ſome parts thereof. And in fine, <hi>Galen,</hi> contrary to the Opinion of all Philoſophers, holds, That Flame, beſides its natural Motion, which is always upwards, has alſo another which makes it ſometimes encline down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; not conſidering, that Flame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver has any ſuch Motion, but when it is forced and conſtrained thereto by Art.</p>
            <p>Nor does the Cenſurer of <hi>Galen</hi> ſtop here, but paſſing on, examins his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, where it ſeems of greateſt weight, that is, in things appertaining to Phyſick. And here he proves, That altho' <hi>Galen</hi> ſeriouſly employed all his Induſtry and Wit therein, yet he penetrated ſo little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and committed ſo many Errors therein, that it would be impoſſible to reckon them up diſtinctly. And ſetting aſide how much his ill Nature obliged him to leave no way untried, that he might obſcure the Fame of the Great <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ſaying, That he obſerved not the ſigns of the Pulſes, nor made any mention of many Feavours, with other like frivolous and vain Objections, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he does not ſo much, as in the leaſt, raſe his skin, altho' he thought to have
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58557:47"/>
grievouſly wounded him; that which ſeems to be moſt important, is, that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf deſignedly to comment on the Writings of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> he ſeems in many places not to underſtand them, often and in many places entangling himſelf, as the Cenſurer diſtinctly ſhews, tho' I, not to be over-tedious, paſs them over. He ſometimes refutes the Diſcourſe of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> but afterwards giving himſelf the Ly, elſewhere commends it, thus mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhewing his little Firmneſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
            <p>He brags moreover, That he had given certain and ſure preſages for the Knowledg of all Diſeaſes: but if others will, yet his moſt cautious Reprover will not in the leaſt believe him herein. For from thoſe few Cures, which, that his Fame might thereby live for ever, he relates himſelf to have performed, it is manifeſtly ſeen, that he never aim'd aright, but was rather greatly miſtaken in the Knowledg of the Diſtempers, and their Cauſes: as in that of the Wife of <hi>Boetus,</hi> and of the Youth, to whom, contrary to the advice of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> he fooliſhly gave Meat in the Augmentation of his Feavor, to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients mortal danger. But peradventure he ſhewed himſelf more ſilly, and mad-man-like,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58557:47"/>
when to regulate the Cure of certain Diſeaſes, he fooliſhly ſought after the Interpretation of idle Dreams. But above all his other Follies that ſeems the greateſt, which he committed in Curing the Wife of <hi>Boetus;</hi> and it is a wonder, that he met not with that Eternal diſgrace and Reproach, which he but too much deſerved for having ſhewn himſelf ſo childiſh and ignorant, running perhaps into as many Errors, as he diviſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</p>
            <p>And finally this ſage Writer concludes againſt <hi>Galen,</hi> That if the great Number of his Volumes were ſifted, there would in this vaſt Bulk be found more Bran than Flower; all that he writes, being paltry Stuff, and idle Prattle, full of vain and high Boaſtings, often intermix'd with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions and Tales, void both of Wit and Senſe; and that they are in fine a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Miſcellany of unwarrantable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, wherein he often enough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats over the ſame thing, altho' he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proteſts, that he would never do it. I paſs over many other, even infinite Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, whereof <hi>Galen</hi> is found guilty by his ſubtil Accuſer, becauſe I think enough has been ſaid to make it eaſily compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended what, and how great were the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58557:48"/>
Conteſts between the Followers of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Greeks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whilſt the Diſputes of the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were proſecuted with the greateſt heat, on a ſudden roſe up the moſt inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Theophraſtus Paracelſus,</hi> who, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing the moſt ancient Method of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, which had for a long time been laid aſide, began attentively to read the great Book of Nature, that he might therein learn the reaſon of Natural Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements. He, intermixing Chimiſtry, wherein he was very skilful, with Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and therewith, as with an uſeful and fit Inſtrument, ſearching into the choiceſt of Natures Secrets, very ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully undertook to cure the moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Diſeaſes with Remedies which he had found out by his Knowledg in this Art. It cannot eaſily be believed, to what an height within a certain ſpace of time his new Sect arrived, either through the new and moſt curious way opened by him to true Philoſophy, or through the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Pleaſantneſs and Efficacy of his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Medicines, or through his happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in Diſeaſes till that time thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable. And the Fame of his skill being now generally ſpread over <hi>Germany, France,</hi> and other Provinces of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58557:48"/>
World, his Doctrines were fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embraced by men well verſed in Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And without doubt the advance of his Glory would have been greater, had he not purpoſely wrapt up and concealed his Doctrine in obſcure Aenigmes, and ambiguous Allegories uſual with Chimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Authors. What and how great were afterwards the Conteſts and Debates, as between thoſe that were only <hi>Galeniſts</hi> and only <hi>Paracelſians,</hi> ſo between thoſe who may be called <hi>Paracelſo-Galeniſts,</hi> and <hi>Galeno-Chimiſts,</hi> is peradventure ſo well known to every one, that I may well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſay any thing thereof. And tho' the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> had enough to do with their extern Enemies, yet were they not, as the Books of that Age teſtifie, very well united, but oftentimes turned their Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities upon themſelves, biting and tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, like ſo many mad Dogs.</p>
            <p>But whilſt <hi>Paracelſus</hi> happily introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vital Anatomy both into Philoſophy and Phyſick; the Anatomy alſo of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals was again brought to light out of the Ruines of Oblivion, wherein it had for a long time lain wholly buried. And the firſt Reſtorer thereof was <hi>Andreas Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalius</hi> of <hi>Bruxells,</hi> a man certainly worthy
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58557:49"/>
of Immortal Fame. He, queſtionleſs a greater Anatomiſt than <hi>Herophilus,</hi> having accuſtomed himſelf from a Child to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſect Rats, and other ſmall Creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come to years of more maturity, by degrees ſearch'd into the ſeveral parts of human Bodies, and relying upon no other Teſtimony, but what was given him by his own Eyes, and his own Hands, clearly manifeſted to every one, in what great Errors the ancient Anatomiſts had lived, and above all, <hi>Galen,</hi> whom he taxes with an hundred and an hundred Faults. It is ſtrange and wonderful to hear, how unmeaſurably he was therefore perſecuted and outraged by the Phyſicians, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries; and how the Diſputes in Phyſick thereby more and more increaſed, there being ſome, who would right or wrong defend and maintain the moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Faults of their Maſter <hi>Galen,</hi> not at all regarding, that they thereby thwarted and went againſt his firſt and principal Sentiment, who rather choſe to incur the danger of Erring with his own Senſes, than blindly to give credit to what he had found related concerning human Bodies by the ancient Anatomiſts, whom he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, tho' wrongfully, blames for their Obſervations about the Entrals of men,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58557:49"/>
becauſe he had ſeen it otherwiſe in thoſe of Monkies.</p>
            <p>But amongſt the fierce and implacable enemies of <hi>Veſſalius,</hi> that famous <hi>Pariſian</hi> Phyſician <hi>Jacobus Silvius</hi> would needs ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize himſelf, and deſirous to contend with him, violently aſſaults him, changing his name <hi>Veſſalius</hi> into <hi>Vaeſanus,</hi> that is, mad, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his book a moſt unworthy, villanous and perplex'd Miſcellany of Errors, and an abominable Dream of filthy and wicked Inſtructions. Then turning to the Readers, he with Prayers and Proteſtations exhorts and conjures them furiouſly to tear it in pieces, and burn it. He beſeeches alſo the Emperor then being, ſeverely to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Author, whom he terms a Monſter of Folly and Ingratitude, an Exemplar of Inſolence and Villany, baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly born, and worſe educated in his Court, ſaying, It would be a deed of Charity, if he totally made him away, and ſtrangled him, that he might not with his poiſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and peſtilential Breath to infect and corrupt the Remainder of <hi>Europe.</hi> Now what more, I pray, could he have done, had poor <hi>Veſſalius</hi> been guilty of High-Treaſon not only againſt Monſieur <hi>Galen,</hi> but even againſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf; or if he had betrayed and ſold <hi>Buda,</hi> or <hi>Alba Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58557:50"/>
to the <hi>Turks;</hi> or if his Writings had been like to thoſe of <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> and impious <hi>Luther?</hi> yet ſo far did the Calumnies and Diffamations of the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Silvius,</hi> and other raſcally <hi>Galeniſts</hi> prevail with the Emperor, who was in all things elſe a moſt juſt Prince, that in fine <hi>Veſſalius</hi> unfortunately loſt his Favour, and was baniſh'd the Court. Thus was that Saying verified, which <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> not yet advanced to the Purple, often had in his mouth; <hi>Saepe bonus, ſaepe cautus decipitur Imperator.</hi> Not long after it appeared, that the Frowardneſs and Spite of <hi>Silvius</hi> paſſed into <hi>Andreas Laurentius,</hi> which made him thus alſo break out againſt the innocent <hi>Veſſalius; Againſt this man let us, as they ſay, put on the Lyons skin, and tame all thoſe monſters, which he has brought forth out of a Spirit of Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo let him undergo the due reward of his Arrogancy and Ingratitude againſt his Maſter</hi> Galen. And perhaps that our Reader of Phyſick, who put into his printed Concluſions theſe moſt elegant words, <hi>The Circulation of the Blood, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with</hi> Harvey <hi>the Author, we utterly reject and explode;</hi> would, if it had been in his power, have done as much for the great <hi>Harvey</hi> with the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58557:50"/>But other learned men little or nothing regarding the diſgrace befaln <hi>Veſſalius,</hi> but rather as is uſual with all great and generous Souls, in whom it is always ſeen, that
<q>Difficulty whets deſire.</q>
being rendred more couragious and eager by the oppoſition, ſet themſelves with their utmoſt endeavour to follow the ſame Track, ſuch as were <hi>Felix Platerus, Gaſper Bauhinus, Gabriel Fallopius, Volcherus, Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Realdus Columbus, Fabritius de Aqua pendente, Adrianus Spigelius,</hi> and many other moſt skilful and induſtrious Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſts, who ſeemed to have arrived to the higheſt pitch of that Art, nothing remaining for a farther ſearch. When behold <hi>Gaſper Aſellius</hi> and <hi>William Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey</hi> (who by the univerſal Conſent of all learned men is reckoned amongſt the greateſt, and moſt expert Anatomiſts of our, or former Ages) publiſhed their new and glorious Inventions, being followed by the nobleſt Company of Phyſicians that ever were in the World, of whom I muſt not omit the moſt famous, as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes Heurnius, Giovanni Picchetti, Thomas Wharton, Ludovicus Bilſius, Nathanael
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58557:51"/>
Heighmore, Francis Gliſſon, Thomas Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholinus, Regnerus Graaf, Carlo Fracaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Richard Lower, Lorenzo Bellini,</hi> and many others, whom for brevity ſake I paſs over, all worthy of immortal praiſe and Renown. Yet muſt I not but make mention of the moſt ingenious <hi>Marcellus Malpighius,</hi>
               <q>The chiefeſt glory of Felſinian ſtreams.</q>
who thirſting after Honour, does ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately practiſe Anatomy in Plants, that nothing more can be deſired in that Art. And in my opinion, it may freely be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that within the narrow compaſs of a few years there have been more Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders diſcovered in the bodies of Animals, than were formerly known in the long courſe of five and thirty Ages: without my taking the boldneſs to ſay, That the finding out alone of the Circulation of the Blood, firſt diſcovered in this our <hi>Italy,</hi> which has always (O great Infelicity of ours)
<q>Fruitful in bringing forth, in cheriſhing ungrateful—</q>
of her Children, and afterwards fully
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58557:51"/>
eſtabliſhed and divulged in <hi>England,</hi> far exceeds the Invention of all Antiquity put together. But of the Queſtions, Quarrels, Contentions, Debates, Diſputes, and Skirmiſhes, that did thereupon ariſe amongſt Phyſicians, I do at preſent for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear any mention; becauſe I well know, we do ſtill with our Eyes behold them. And perhaps it is manifeſt to every one, how that <hi>Primeroſe, Pariſani,</hi> and <hi>Riola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Junior (who was in all things elſe an acute Anatomiſt) pertinaciouſly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Non-circulation of the Blood, being ſcoff'd at, and baffled by the moſt famous Scholars of <hi>Europe,</hi> were forced at laſt ſhamefully to recant their Follies; and that <hi>Vopiſcus Fortunatus Pemplius,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt briskly oppoſed the Circulation of the Blood, being afterwards convinced and refuted by the Great <hi>Renatus des Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and <hi>John Wallis</hi> more accurately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing his Works anew, he finally ſang this famous Palinody; <hi>At firſt the Invention pleaſed me not, as by my Diſcourſes and Writings I have publickly teſtified: But the more I laboured to refute and condemn it, the more I condemn, and refute my ſelf; his reaſons being not only ſo perſwaſive, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive.</hi> I know very well, that there are at this day ſome, who, conſidering the reproach and diſhonour that befel <hi>Prime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58557:52"/>
and <hi>Pariſani,</hi> and ſeeing all thoſe learned men, which either publiſh Books in Print, or with eſteem read Lectures in their Univerſities, unanimouſly do admit of theſe Modern Diſcoveries, and therefore not daring in the preſence of Scholars to contradict any of them, do yet amongſt thoſe, who are wholly ignorant of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, covertly mutter and murmure, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently preſuming to ſay, That ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny different things cannot any way be in the bodies of Animals; that, if they were there, their <hi>Galen</hi> was not ſo ſimple or fooliſh, but that he, long before theſe Modern Inventors appeared in the World, would diſtinctly have diſcerned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them: foraſmuch as being moſt accurate and ingenious, and having given all Phyſick its laſt and perfect Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is not credible, that he ſhould in this alone have ſo groſsly erred: wherefore it is not neceſſary for us to beat our Brains about theſe new Inventions in Medicine, ſeeing we ought to rely upon his Labours, and ſatisfie our ſelves with a full under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his Sentiments, Reaſons, and Oracles, ſo they call his moſt Witleſs and vain Expreſſions. And in fine they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That we ought blindfoldly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Galen,</hi> and ſome other ancient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, even tho' our Senſes ſometimes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58557:52"/>
that theſe are often wont to deceive us, which thoſe men will not do, who, having ſpent their whole life in Study and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, have all along been by every one reput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Gods of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>But for my part, I ſhall not, to convince, and undeceive them, give my ſelf the trouble manifeſtly to ſhew them (as I could well do) that do give more credit to authority &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, than to our Senſes, is the moſt fooliſh Obſtinacy that could ever fall into the mind of man: foraſmuch as I imagine that to get clear of ſuch Straits, they would reject the cleareſt Demonſtrations of the Modern Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. I ſhall therefore only briefly let them know, how little they underſtand the very Sentiments of their Maſters. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they never much regarded that moſt true Saying of their own <hi>Ariſtotle; That we ought to give credit to Reaſon, if the things of Reaſon agree with Experience:</hi> Nor yet that other Saying of the ſame Author; <hi>That to forſake the Guidance of our Senſes, to be blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly led by Reaſon, is a great Argument of the weakneſs of our Wit.</hi> And was not <hi>Galen</hi> alſo of the ſame mind? See here his own Words; <hi>all thoſe are rather to be eſteemed fooliſh, than wiſe, who being able fully to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and perceive things by their Senſes, will yet avow, that we cannot learn but by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations alone.</hi> And in another place
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58557:53"/>
the ſame Author ſaith; <hi>The Doctrine of thoſe that rely upon the Sayings of others, is tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, and full of Confuſion and Debates.</hi> And in Gods Name let them read alſo the ſame Sentiment in their <hi>Avicen;</hi> and if they be not yet ſatisfied, let them go, and learn of the Prince of Divines, <hi>Joannes Scotus,</hi> where he ſaith, That all thoſe who will not credit their Senſes, juſtly deſerve to be burnt. And let them know farther, that whoever has the leaſt ſpark of Reaſon, of what Sect ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be, muſt needs ſay, as doth that great Light of <hi>Galenical</hi> and <hi>Hippocratical</hi> Phyſick, <hi>Nicolaus Leonicenus; We ought not ſo far to foregoe our own Judgments, as always to follow the foot-ſteps of others, and to be certain our ſelves of nothing: For this would be to ſee with other mens Eyes, to hear with other mens Ears, and ſmell with other mens Noſes, and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with other mens Intelligence, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our ſelves no other than meer ſtones, to commit all things to the aſſertions of others, and not to believe our ſelves able to make any true diſcuſſion in doubtful matters</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And another of <hi>Galens</hi> Followers exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly condemning this ſame pertinacy, relates a very pleaſant adventure, to wit, That a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain publick Reader, long time verſed, and grown old in the Books of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> being one day by chance preſent at an Anatomy, and clearly ſeeing, that the <hi>Vena cava</hi> takes
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58557:53"/>
its Original from the innumerable Threds or Roots which are in the Liver, full of wonder and aſtoniſhment,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As one that never beheld a thing incredible.</hi> confeſs'd indeed, by what his Senſes ſhewed him, the <hi>Vena cava</hi> muſt deſcend from the Liver; but that he ought not therefore by crediting his Senſes to contradict his Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who conſtantly affirms, all the veins in mans body to have their beginning from the Heart; becauſe, ſaid he, it is much more eaſie for our Senſes to be ſometimes deceived, than for the Great and Soveraign <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ever to have faln into any Error. And ſo much Power had his Obſtinacy over him, that being in the company of certain learned men, ſhewn by one of them a little Suet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Heart, which melted by the faint heat of a Candle, to defend his <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> by whom this is denied, he durſt to ſay, that what he ſaw, was not Fat,</p>
            <p>And certainly pleaſant enough is that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo which is related by the moſt famous <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> that one, who was deeply read in the Writings of the <hi>Peripateticks,</hi> becauſe he would not be compell'd to confeſs, that the Stars, and other new things diſcovered in the Heavens by the great <hi>Galileo,</hi> were true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the aſſiſtance of the Teleſcope; and that another, yet more obſtinate, would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to ſee him open one of thoſe little
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58557:54"/>
Frogs, which in Summer are ſeen in the duſty High-ways, for fear of being obliged to confeſs, that they are not engendred in the inſtant of the Drops being incorporated with the Duſt. But where ſhall I have room to relate the Diſputes and Conteſts which grew up in <hi>Rome</hi> about the Medicinal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that famous Phyſician <hi>Proſper Martianus?</hi> Who being endued with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Learning, and prudent Sagacity, and gloriouſly employing the utmoſt of his Ability and Induſtry in ſearching into the Doctrine of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> manifeſtly ſhews, that <hi>Galen</hi> oftentimes either did not, or would not comprehend the true Sentiments of that venerable old man. And <hi>Petro Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li,</hi> avouching the ſame thing, tells us beſides, That <hi>Galen</hi> took the ſame courſe in explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt learned Opinions of the divine <hi>Plato: Galen either underſtood not, or would not underſtand</hi> Hippocrates <hi>or</hi> Plato, <hi>to give the greater eſteem to his own Writings.</hi> Then he defends the moſt wiſe Old Man from his Reproofs and Taunts, eſpecially about the Cauſes of Feavers, conſtantly affirming, not only that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> never preſcribed the letting of Blood in Feavers, but where the exceſſive internal Inflammation required it, as was alſo before him fully obſerved by <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus Cardanus;</hi> but farthemore aſſerting, That according to the Doctrine of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58557:54"/>
a Feaver is one of thoſe Diſtempers, which in nowiſe admits of Phlebotomy. Theſe and other good and ſound Doctrines the learned <hi>Martianus</hi> wiſely manifeſting, revived with them the decayed, and almoſt extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd Sect of his dear <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I know not how I have hitherto for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore to mention one, who, altho a woman, deſerves yet to be reckoned amongſt the greateſt Scholars, I mean the Lady <hi>Donna O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liva Sabuco,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>She childiſh ſports, and Female Exerciſe</l>
                  <l>Ev'n from her tender years did ſtill deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>To ſpin, or to the Needle ſet her hand,</l>
                  <l>Of maſculine learning ſtudious, ſhe diſdain'd.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſhe being abundantly furniſhed with more than maſculine Wit, and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, couragiouſly imployed both her Brains and Mind in the Inveſtigation of Natural things; and advancing in her Studies, ſhe ſet her wits upon things of greateſt uſe, and to the end <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Whole might receive ſome benefit thereby, ſhe wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave beginning to a new and moſt inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious way of Curing. And writing a Letter to the moſt auguſt Monarch <hi>Philip</hi> the Second, of Eternal and Glorious Memory, ſhe thus diſplays her Wit. <hi>It is as plain as the light of the Sun, That the ancient Phyſick was in an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, according as it is read and practiſed in its principal Fundamentals, for that the ancient
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58557:55"/>
Philoſophers and Phyſicians neither underſtood or reach'd the true nature upon which Phyſick is founded, and from whence it draws its original; of which, not only the underſtanding Chriſtian Phyſicians may be Judges, but alſo thoſe that have any proſpect into other Faculties, being perſons of Wit and Judgment.</hi> And a little after. <hi>He that cannot comprehend or underſtand it, let him leave it to others that are to come, or let him believe Experience, and not the ancient Phyſick. Therefore my Petition is juſt, that theſe my Followers may be approved for one year, ſince they have tryed the Rules of</hi> Galen <hi>and</hi> Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates <hi>for theſe</hi> 2000 <hi>years, and have found the Effect ſo inconſiderable, and the Ends ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, as is to be ſeen every day, and was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd in the paſt Epidemic Catarrhs, Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Feavers, Small Pox, and Peſtilences, and many other Infirmities; in the Cure of which, that ſort of Phyſick is ſo ineffectual, that ſcarce two in a thouſand live out the natural Limits of life; but all die violent deaths of ſome Diſeaſe or other, without any Remedy from ancient Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in her Dialogue of True Phyſick: <hi>You cannot deny (Mr. Doctor) but that the Phyſick you uſe, is uncertain, various, and fallacious, and that its End and Effects are falſe and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious, whereas we ſee the ends and effects of other Arts to be certain, and true without variation; as in Arithmetick, Geometry, Muſick, Aſcro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which bring to paſs the end and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58557:55"/>
which they purpoſe. Which end fails, as you ſee in Phyſick, being ſo deceitful, uncertain, and various. Whence it muſt follow, that this Art fails in its firſt grounds and foundations, becauſe it produces not fruit conformable to what it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; ſo that when we expect Currans, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Apples, it brings forth nothing but Galls and Medlars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a little further, maintaining the ſame Opinion, ſhe ſaies; <hi>You cannot deny, Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the Inconſtancy of Phyſick, and how many alterations have been made in it, and that the Art was for a long time forbidden in</hi> Rome, <hi>where thoſe wiſe people gave no credit to it, nor would ſeek for Cure from the hands of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, for the reaſons I have ſaid, which are of great efficacy. Neither did the</hi> Saracens, <hi>nor thoſe of</hi> China <hi>admit Phyſicians. And thoſe grave and ancient Authors themſelves Cry out, that Life is ſhort, Art long, Judgment difficult, and Experience dangerous. And</hi> Hippocrates, <hi>That no certain and perfect aſſurance in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick can be attained to. Nor can you deny, Mr. Doctor, but that they were men as we are, or that their Sayings were not above the Condition of Men, but that they ſpoke according to Nature, which aſpired no higher than what the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe of man could reach. Therefore,</hi> ſaies Pliny, <hi>there is no Art in the World ſo inconſtant as that of Phyſick, which changes every day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Donna Oliva</hi> goes on farther,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58557:56"/>
whoſe excellent parts is not my intent now to ſum up, and reckon, ſince the doing thereof would hold me o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver long. I ſhall content my ſelf therefore to mention, that ſome of the moſt famous Authors have laid claim to many things, falſely boaſting, themſelves to have been the firſt Diſcoverers of them (as about the manner, which Nature uſes in diſtributing the Aliment to all the Parts of an animated Body) whereof ſhe had full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge long before, and gloriouſly publiſh'd them in her Books.</p>
            <p>After her there aroſe in our <hi>Italy</hi> a new Syſtem of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Phyſick, which was the laudable Invention of that famous Philoſopher, and Doctor in Divinity, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Campanella.</hi> He never practiſed Phyſick, but yet would ſearch into the moſt ſecret <hi>Arcanum</hi>'s thereof: And as it was eaſie for his more than ordinary Wit to ſeparate his Philoſophy from the vulgar, commonly taught in the Schools: ſo alſo he wanted not skill with ſpecious Doctrines to eſtabliſh another Invention of Rational Phyſick, from whence again followed many various Diſputes and Contentions in the Art.</p>
            <p>But O how far were they in our days out-ſtrip'd by that Great <hi>Hermes</hi> of the lower <hi>Germany, John Baptiſt van Helmont,</hi> who, being endued with more ſublime and noble Parts, attempted a great Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, whence Debates and Oppoſitions mightily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. He, accompanying the Vivacity of his Wit with a ſingular Morality, and curiouſly applying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Chimiſtry, wholly bent his Studies to the ſolving of Natural Bodies, and ſparing no ſort of Pains or Charge, ſurmounted to ſuch an height, that leaving far behind him the glorious ſteps of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus,</hi> he never ſtopt, till he had happily arrived to finiſh a wonderful, and never-before-heard-of Syſtem of Rational Phyſick.</p>
            <p>And in like manner have we ſeen in our Days the famous <hi>Thomas Willis</hi> with his new Syſtem of Rational Phyſick advancing apace along the path of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58557:56"/>
Immortality and Glory: Nor is it eaſie to believe, with what Diligence he endeavoured to collect all that he deemed neceſſary for ſo Noble a Work; nor yet what Pains he took, what Watchings he underwent, and what Eagerneſs he uſed to bring it to its entire Perfection. Nor was leſs Trouble un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone, or leſs Induſtry uſed in a like Uundertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>Silvius,</hi> famous for the innumerable Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Followers, as <hi>Gliſſon Helvetius, Meſſonier, Travagino,</hi> and other illuſtrious Scholars of this Age: Many of which, I know not for what reaſon, have not yet publiſh'd their Conceptions. I ſay nothing at preſent of thoſe able men who yet ſweat at the work, and hope, by the Aſſiſtance of the Modern Anatomiſts, and new Natural Philoſophy, to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their generous Deſigns concerning various Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtems of Rational Phyſick. And I paſs by alſo thoſe who ingeniouſly empty themſelves in deviſing Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtems of Experimental and Methodical Phyſick, but ſuch as greatly varies, and differs from that of the Ancients. But how much the Quarrel of Phyſicians are thereby encreaſed, to the overturning and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuring all Medicine, is not neceſſary to be named at preſent, ſince we plainly ſee it before our Eyes. Wherefore if the moſt Eloquent <hi>Pliny</hi> were living in theſe our days, he would certainly more angrily than ever cry out; <hi>Mutatur Ars quotidie toties interpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp; ingeniorum flatu impellimur,</hi> not indeed by the Wits of <hi>Greece,</hi> now lying idle, and ſervile under the Yoak of the <hi>Barbarians;</hi> but the moſt famous ones of <hi>England,</hi> and other Provinces, by him in his time eſteemed Barbarous.</p>
            <p>But I now at laſt ſee my ſelf encompaſs'd about with a moſt innumerable Troop of Phyſicians, by whom Phyſick is divided into ſo many Factions, and ſhivered, as it were, into ſo many pieces, that it is impoſſible for the Wit of man to part it into more. And theſe are all men, who will not follow the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58557:57"/>
ſteps of either <hi>Greek, Latin, Barbarian,</hi> or other Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Writer, whether Ancient or Modern, nor be always tied to the Sentiments of any; but being free, and diſengaged, ſwiftly over-run the moſt vaſt Kingdoms of Nature, and then oppugning the moſt difficult and obſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Diſeaſes, with Arms gotten by their own Labours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d not borrowed, or taken from the Arſenals of ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, nor unskilfully managed, know how to render their Names eternally illuſtrious by their glorious Undertakings. Thus crediting nothing but what they perceive by their own Senſes, or have approved by moſt certain Experience, they will look into all, penetrate all, and with a curious Eye nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly examine all, not allowing any Reaſon for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, but only what agrees with the Sagacity of their own Underſtanding. And thus being contrary to all Sects, and not wholly Enemies to any of the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, they proteſt, that they herein follow the ſteps of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> more, than their moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Defenders. And foraſmuch as I think it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to our purpoſe, to ſee whether ſuch a Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ought to be permitted them: I beſeech you, Gentlemen, at our next Meeting to hear their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſince what I have already ſaid, may ſuffice for the preſent.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THis is the firſt Diſcourſe of <hi>Signor Lionardo di Capoa,</hi> who hath writ ſeven others upon the ſame ſubject: which according to the acceptance this meets with in Publick, ſhall likewiſe be Engliſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58557:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
